<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-08-14T19:37:54-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><entry><title type="html">Replication Markets: Can You Predict Which Social Science Papers Will Replicate?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/replication-markets/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Replication Markets: Can You Predict Which Social Science Papers Will Replicate?" /><published>2019-08-21T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-08-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/replication-markets</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/replication-markets/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-are-replication-markets&quot;&gt;What are Replication Markets?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Replication Markets are a type of &lt;a href=&quot;http://mason.gmu.edu/~rhanson/ideafutures.html&quot;&gt;prediction market&lt;/a&gt;, mechanisms that enable individuals to bet on the outcome of events. Just as financial markets efficiently determine the perceived value of a security by aggregating the beliefs of buyers and sellers (e.g., I think this stock will rise in price, so I will buy more), &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/p/prediction-market.asp&quot;&gt;prediction markets&lt;/a&gt; determine the perceived likelihood of an event by aggregating the beliefs of many individuals. Both financial and prediction markets draw on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wisdom_of_the_crowd&quot;&gt;wisdom&lt;/a&gt; (or sometimes lunacy) of crowds and the power of financial incentives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many demonstrated applications of prediction markets, like predicting political events (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.predictit.org&quot;&gt;PredictIt&lt;/a&gt; enables betting on who will be the Democratic nominee in the 2020 US election).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Replication Markets are another such application, and they will be the focus of this article. Replication Markets aggregate predictions about which scientific claims will successfully replicate (i.e., demonstrate a statistically significant effect when the experiment is repeated). Replication markets for social science research have a track record of success, reaching upwards of 75% accuracy and sometimes even surpassing the predictive performance of experts (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pnas.org/content/112/50/15343&quot;&gt;this paper&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0167487018303283&quot;&gt;this other paper&lt;/a&gt;, or the papers &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.citationfuture.com/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, for example).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A DARPA project called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.darpa.mil/program/systematizing-confidence-in-open-research-and-evidence&quot;&gt;SCORE&lt;/a&gt; (Systematizing Confidence in Open Research and Evidence) intends to use prediction markets to forecast if social science research claims will replicate. 3000 such claims will be in the market. &lt;a href=&quot;https://predict.replicationmarkets.com/main/#!/about&quot;&gt;The claims&lt;/a&gt; come “from social and behavioral science articles published in the last 10 years” (psychology, economics, education research, management and marketing, political science, and sociology and criminology).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a public website, &lt;a href=&quot;http://replicationmarkets.com&quot;&gt;Replication Markets&lt;/a&gt; (RM), that is crowdsourcing these predictions for SCORE. Nearly anyone can participate and there are financial rewards for top forecasters. (When I refer to RM, I’m referring to the contest the site is currently hosting.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this essay, I’ll explain how RM works, explain the market mechanisms and game theory of it, and walk through my thought process and strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-replication-markets-works&quot;&gt;How &lt;em&gt;Replication Markets&lt;/em&gt; Works&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-counts-as-replication&quot;&gt;What Counts as Replication?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I myself am participating in the RM game. Because I’m competitive, I want to keep score. Though the total financial rewards sum to over $100k, realistically the chance of anyone person winning a lot of money is pretty low, so I’m doing this mostly for fun. Nonetheless, I’ll use money as my metric for success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To win money, we need to predict replication. To do that, we need to know what the criterion for replication is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.replicationmarkets.com/index.php/2019/06/24/what-is-high-powered-replication/&quot;&gt;According to Replication Markets&lt;/a&gt;, for each of the claims (i.e., the social science assertions) selected to be tested, SCORE’s data team “will run a single high-quality replication of each selected claim.” A replication will be &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.replicationmarkets.com/index.php/frequently-asked-questions/&quot;&gt;deemed successful&lt;/a&gt; if they get a statistically significant result in the same direction as the original claim. Markets for claims are binary: ultimately, each claim will either replicate or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;format-of-the-game&quot;&gt;Format of the Game&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Replication Markets is composed of 10, 4-week rounds, starting in September 2019 (plus a special Round 0 for meta-claims in August 2019, which I’ll address later). &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.replicationmarkets.com/index.php/frequently-asked-questions/payouts/&quot;&gt;Each round has two components&lt;/a&gt;: markets and surveys, both of which are ways to aggregate many opinions and achieve the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?q=wisdom+of+crowds&amp;amp;rlz=1C1CHBF_enUS851US851&amp;amp;oq=wsidom+of+c&amp;amp;aqs=chrome.1.69i57j0l5.3192j1j0&amp;amp;sourceid=chrome&amp;amp;ie=UTF-8&quot;&gt;wisdom of crowds.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Surveys&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surveys are private evaluations (i.e., opinion polls) of the probability that a given claim is true. These evaluations are made a week prior to the market’s opening. Surveys come in batches of 10 claims (all from the same journal, I believe), and there are around 15 per round. Surveys pay out at the end of the following round, with top 4 participants receiving \$80, \$40, \$20, and \$20 dollars each.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RM isn’t specifying how exactly the surveys will be scored. Because they resolve a month after closing, before the actual replication attempts, they must involve predicting what probabilities the prediction markets will give each claim. I emailed RM to find out about the scoring and was told this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;wp-block-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    There is actually an extensive academic literature studying more sophisticated and in many ways superior methods of aggregating crowd forecasts. We are experimenting with such cutting edge methods. In other words, &lt;strong&gt;in the survey you are scored against our best judgment of the right forecast, having processed all the forecasts of other participants using our best aggregation techniques. &lt;/strong&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
  
  &lt;cite&gt;Personal Communication&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Markets&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Markets are the prediction market aspect of RM. Each participant is given a set number of points, which she can use to buy Yes or No shares for a claim. Markets “pay out proportionally to winning shares” and will resolve by mid-2020, once the replications have been attempted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.replicationmarkets.com/index.php/frequently-asked-questions/rules/&quot;&gt;rules&lt;/a&gt;, only 100 of the 3000 (i.e., 3.33%) claims will be selected &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; pay out (these claims will be directly replicated; the data-replicated claims do not pay out). Each of these has a total payout of \$900, paid proportional to the number of winning shares in a resolved claim (e.g., I have 10 Yes shares for Claim X; the total number of Yes shares held by RM participants in 1,000; so, I am paid 10/1,000 out of \$900, which equals \$9).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the meta round, Round 0, “Meta-claims resolve as the proportion of successful direct replications, so a meta-claim resolving as 60% would pay 0.6 points per ‘Yes’ share and 0.4 points per ‘No’ share.” The total payout for this round is $360 for each of the 12 meta-claims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pricing-and-game-theory-for-markets&quot;&gt;Pricing and Game Theory for Markets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-are-shares-priced&quot;&gt;How Are Shares Priced?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike traditional financial markets that use a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Double_auction&quot;&gt;Double Auction process&lt;/a&gt;, if you want to buy/sell a share of a claim in RM, you don’t need someone on the other end of the transaction willing to sell/buy at that price. Rather, in RM you buy directly from the market manager using a pricing system developed by Robin Hanson, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://mason.gmu.edu/~rhanson/mktscore.pdf&quot;&gt;Logarithmic Market Scoring Rules&lt;/a&gt; (LMSR)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LMSR made no sense to me when I first learned about it. And frankly, it doesn’t totally make sense to me now. Robin Hanson wrote a couple of papers on it, so look into them if you want to deeply understand it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I’m not a finance guy, I don’t care enough to understand it deeply. Most of my knowledge I’ve gleaned from the equations &lt;a href=&quot;http://beza1e1.tuxen.de/articles/LMSR.html&quot;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt; These are, in my opinion, the important points:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The price of buying shares at time &lt;em&gt;t&lt;/em&gt; depends on the cost of the share at time &lt;em&gt;t-1&lt;/em&gt;; the cost of the share changes after every trade.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The cost of shares depends on how many ‘Yes’ and ‘No’ shares have been bought. The market’s prediction of a claim (i.e., its price), p, depends on the number of ‘Yes’ and ‘No’ shares bought. p is equal to the market’s probability rating of the claim.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘Yes’ shares get cheaper as p decreases whereas ‘No’ shares get more expensive, and vice versa.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The relationship between p and the cost of a ‘Yes’ or ‘No’ share is essentially linear or slightly concave upward or downward, depending on if you’re buying minority or majority shares.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-to-win-the-markets&quot;&gt;How to Win the Markets&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game-theoretic aspect of RM is that the price of a ‘Yes’ or ‘No’ share depends on the market’s evaluation of that claim, which can change volatilely. This presents the opportunity for arbitrage, especially in Round 0.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As one participant in RM explains:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;wp-block-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    If you buy &amp;#8220;yes&amp;#8221; when the market is at 30% then sell when it is at 50% you end up with more points. Of course, points are only useful for buying shares in other markets, so you should only &amp;#8220;cash out profits&amp;#8221; if you think there&amp;#8217;s another market that is further off than the one you&amp;#8217;re cashing out of.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  
  &lt;cite&gt;&amp;#8211; &lt;a href=&quot;https://predict.replicationmarkets.com/main/#!/users/188&quot;&gt;Davidoj&lt;/a&gt;, RM participant&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s an example of arbitrage, converting 23 ‘No’ shares to 36 ‘Yes’ shares (with the help of 2 other points, which buy about 6 of the 36 shares):&lt;figure class=&quot;wp-block-image&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt; 
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/arbitrage_1.png&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; display=&quot;block&quot; margin=&quot;0 auto&quot; /&gt; 
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/arbitrage_2.png&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; display=&quot;block&quot; margin=&quot;0 auto&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Round 0&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For Round 0, you must predict the percentage of claims that will replicate per field and per time period. There are 12 such “meta-claims”. Pay outs are based on the number of ‘Yes’ or ‘No’ shares you have for each of these 12 meta-claims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To determine the proper strategy and expected payout, we must consider the following parameters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;N = the number of total RM participants (as of August 2019, the site claims 500 people have signed up; however, it seems only a 100 or so people are actively participating in the markets; this bodes well, as the fewer participants, the greater your chances of winning.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The number of points (participants start with 100)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The proportion of N that spend all their points (I’ll assume this is 100% to be conservative)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A toy example: assume that every meta-claim had a replication rate of 50%. This means that ‘Yes’ and ‘No’ shares are paid the same amount. The total prize money is \$4320 for these 12 claims. The total pool of points is 50,000, assuming N = 500. So, if everyone bought their shares at the exact same price, each point is worth about \$0.086. Given that everyone started with 100 points, each person earns around \$8.60. If we change our assumptions and let N = 100, each person earns around \$43.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A more realistic example: assume that each meta-claim has a 0.5 chance of being either 40% or 60%. Suppose that you end up being on the correct side of all 12 of these markets (i.e., if the replication rate is 60%, you bought all ‘Yes’ shares). Also, suppose that the prediction market’s final estimates for all these claims are 50%. Then, if you start with 100 points and evenly distribute them across claims, your earnings will be around 10% more, as you receive 0.6 points for every “correct” share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Strategy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are possible arbitrage and subterfuge opportunities, but frankly, I don’t think they’re worth going into given how small the rewards are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rounds 1-10&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more interesting game theory is in Rounds 1-10. Should we uniformly distribute our points, or should we focus on areas in which we have more expertise, and therefore are more likely to correctly predict?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Replication Markets &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.replicationmarkets.com/index.php/2019/06/24/what-to-do/&quot;&gt;suggests&lt;/a&gt; the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The market is probably most accurate when forecasters specialize, because one kind of forecaster won’t have enough points.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Per round, each forecaster has 300 points to spend on 300 claims, 10 of which will be directly replicated and paid out. Assuming (obviously a simplification) that replication rate is constant across all six fields, that means around 1.67 claims per field will be directly replicated each round. The total prizes per round are \$9000, meaning that the expected prize money for each claim is \$30.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Strategy&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conditional on a claim being selected for replication and you predicting the correct outcome, the fewer the number of participants in that market, the higher your payout. &lt;strong&gt;So, your best option is to participate in the markets that have the fewest participants (such a rule wouldn’t function in a traditional double auction financial market, but in RM it works because you buy shares from the market manager).&lt;/strong&gt; Other than that, there isn’t much strategy to give at the individual level (prediction markets are about aggregate behavior, after all).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Note, however, that this isn’t an evolutionarily stable strategy; if everyone were to realize markets with fewer participants increased their chances of winning, the equilibrium condition would be an even distribution of participants among all markets.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-to-win-the-surveys&quot;&gt;How to Win the Surveys&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surveys are by far the more financially rewarding opportunity in RM. They have a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.truepoker.eu/poker-tournaments/payout-structure/&quot;&gt;tournament payout structure&lt;/a&gt;, with only the top 4 forecasters winning. And they don’t involve the confusing LMSR the markets use. To win the surveys, you need to be good at predicting which claims will replicate, which I’ll focus on below. But first, let’s focus on the second-order function of which claims the rest of the survey-takers &lt;em&gt;believe&lt;/em&gt; will replicate, as this is key to the survey scoring function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;issues-in-survey-incentive-design&quot;&gt;Issues in Survey Incentive Design&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RM will use some secret crowd aggregation technique for scoring surveys. All they’re willing to reveal is that “in the survey you are scored against our best judgment of the right forecast, having processed all the forecasts of other participants using our best aggregation techniques.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I imagine that if you want to win the surveys, your private survey opinions must align with the aggregate survey predictions. Setting aside any sort of nested/higher-order logic on the part of other survey participants (e.g., if everyone adopted a strategy of biasing their survey results towards what they thought everyone else would say, that strategy wouldn’t work), how could we optimally align our survey answers?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This depends on the survey scoring method. A good candidate is to be found in the recent arXiv paper by Yang Liu and Yiling Chen (two members of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.replicationmarkets.com/index.php/our-team/&quot;&gt;RM scoring team&lt;/a&gt;), “&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/1802.09158.pdf&quot;&gt;Surrogate Scoring Rules and a Uniform Dominant Truth Serum&lt;/a&gt;“. Considering that RM will be experimenting with novel methods of survey aggregation, I think this fits the bill. The question is: will understanding the scoring system allow us to game it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Surrogate Scoring Rules&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scoring problem Liu and Chen address is the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to aggregate the opinions of many individuals, you must &lt;strong&gt;elicit&lt;/strong&gt; these opinions and &lt;strong&gt;verify&lt;/strong&gt; them. In markets, for example, opinions are elicited by the prospect of financial reward and verified against the ground truth (whether or not a security’s price rises or falls). An agent’s &lt;strong&gt;score&lt;/strong&gt; is how well his prediction matches the ground truth. These are called “&lt;strong&gt;Strictly Proper Scoring Rules&lt;/strong&gt;” (SPSR). Under an SPSR, an agent is expected to maximize his expected score and truthfully reveal his beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conversely, situations in which verification is noisy or unavailable (e.g., Replication Markets, as we won’t know if the claims replicate until mid-2020) are called “&lt;strong&gt;Information Elicitation Without Verification&lt;/strong&gt;” (IEWV), and they face a host of issues. A family of &lt;em&gt;peer prediction&lt;/em&gt; mechanisms has been developed to deal with these issues. One such issue is that because an agent’s score depends on the beliefs of others, an agent can benefit from misrepresenting his beliefs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question for the principal (i.e., RM) is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;wp-block-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    Can we design scoring mechanisms to quantify the quality of information as SPSR do and achieve truthful elicitation in a certain form of dominant strategy for IEWV?
  &lt;/p&gt;
  
  &lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/1802.09158.pdf&quot;&gt;Liu and Chen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of their proposed solutions is “surrogate scoring rules” (SSR).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Hansons’ LMSR makes a bit of sense to me, SSR makes absolutely no sense at this time. One might be able to derive some value from really digging into this topic, but I think honestly representing your opinions offers a pretty optimal strategy for the surveys. Just give your honest belief about if a claim will replicate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To that end, how should we predict if a claim will replicate?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-replication-crisis-and-our-base-rate-of-replication&quot;&gt;The Replication Crisis and Our Base Rate of Replication&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we want to predict which studies will replicate, we first need a base rate of replication among all social science. To determine this, we must ask ourselves: is social science actually science? Some are skeptical:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;
    The core of the problem:&lt;br /&gt;1) social scientists want to &amp;#8220;learn statistics&amp;#8221; w/o understanding probability.&lt;br /&gt;2) social science is NOT science. &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/k064zytNBB&quot;&gt;https://t.co/k064zytNBB&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;— Nassim Nicholas Taleb (@nntaleb) 
  
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/nntaleb/status/881500380479279104?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;July 2, 2017&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though I’m not Taleb-level skeptical, I believe there’s an inkling of truth in his claim that many academics are “&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/incerto/the-intellectual-yet-idiot-13211e2d0577&quot;&gt;intellectuals-yet-idiots&lt;/a&gt;” who lack “&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/incerto/what-do-i-mean-by-skin-in-the-game-my-own-version-cc858dc73260&quot;&gt;skin in the game&lt;/a&gt;” (though Taleb himself is an IYI on topics like behavioral genetics and psychometrics). Evidence includes the following list of social science and medicine research areas and claims that were once taken seriously but have failed to replicate:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2019/05/07/5-httlpr-a-pointed-review/&quot;&gt;candidate gene era&lt;/a&gt; in psychology/genetics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/681700v2&quot;&gt;early, small N&lt;/a&gt; work done in &lt;a href=&quot;http://tomstafford.staff.shef.ac.uk/reliable/IsCognitiveNeurosciencereliable.html&quot;&gt;cognitive neuroscience&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Much of nutritional research and epidemiology, the methods of which are extremely suspect (e.g., doing a proper RCT is nearly impossible, retrospective food tracking is unreliable, genetic confounding, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The social psychology literature on priming, which is p-hacked and riddled with publication bias&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The educational research on &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Russwarne/status/1152857329181704192&quot;&gt;growth mindset&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The effect of early-childhood educational interventions on academic outcomes (which has &lt;a href=&quot;https://rpubs.com/EmilOWK/pub_bias_early_intervention&quot;&gt;clear publication bias&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/nrd3439-c1&quot;&gt;Candidate drug targets&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22460880?dopt=Abstract&amp;amp;holding=npg&quot;&gt;oncology&lt;/a&gt;; one replication effort had a 6/53 &lt;strong&gt;(~11%) replication rate&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This list doesn’t inspire confidence. Ex post facto, it’s easy to call these fields BS and impugn the motivations of the researchers doing the spurious research within them. (And sure, some of these fields still suffer from collective delusions inspired by political ideology.) But in most cases, we should remember &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hanlon%27s_razor&quot;&gt;Hanlon’s razor&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;wp-block-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    &amp;#8220;Never attribute to malice that which is adequately explained by stupidity.&amp;#8221;
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, frankly, I don’t think we can chalk it all up to stupidity. All the list of failed replications demonstrates is that the social science publishing game has a lot of &lt;strong&gt;perverse incentives&lt;/strong&gt;. For example, there’s a massive &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Principal%E2%80%93agent_problem&quot;&gt;principal-agent problem&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: the incentives of the agent—the researcher who wants to get tenure and publish novel findings—do not necessarily align with those of the principal—humanity as a whole, which (in theory) has much to gain from the public good, science, that the agent is contributing to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consequently, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malpractice&quot;&gt;academic malpractice&lt;/a&gt;—whether due to malfeasance, obstinance, or negligence—is much more common then we think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;These failures of social science and ethics notwithstanding, and despite claims that&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://robotics.cs.tamu.edu/RSS2015NegativeResults/pmed.0020124.pdf&quot;&gt;most published research findings might be false&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;, large parts of social science &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; replicable.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Case in point, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41562-018-0399-z&quot;&gt;2018 replication project&lt;/a&gt; for 21 social science papers published in &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; (two of the top general science journals) between 2010 and 2015 had a replication rate of 62%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;does-replication-rate-vary-significantly-by-field&quot;&gt;Does Replication Rate Vary Significantly By Field?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A single general social science replication project is useful, but certainly not dispositive. A much better approach is to look at replication on a field-by-field basis, set these as our priors, and forecast replication of specific claims using these priors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s clear that certain fields have better &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.lesswrong.com/wiki/Epistemic_hygiene&quot;&gt;epistemic hygiene&lt;/a&gt; than others. One index of poor epistemic hygiene is the percentage of publications in a field that feature results confirming the tested hypothesis, i.e., positive results. Psychology &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2850928/&quot;&gt;is the worst culprit&lt;/a&gt; in this regard. &lt;figure class=&quot;wp-block-image&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt; 
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/positive_publication_bias-1.jpg&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; max-width=&quot;100%&quot; display=&quot;block&quot; margin=&quot;0 auto&quot; alt=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2850928/&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typically, among the social sciences, it’s the “harder” social sciences (e.g., much of economics, parts of psychology like behavioral genetics and quantitative psychology) that have better epistemic hygiene. Therefore, we’d expect replication to be higher in these fields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I’d like to put concrete estimates on the replication rates and rank-order the fields. To do this, I’ll consider the following for each field:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Replication rates from existing replication efforts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Any indices of publication bias&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How strong the culture of replication is&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How much dissent and debate is tolerated&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How mathematical each field is (which isn’t to say mathematical models are better—excessive math is often a form of formalist obscurantism, and dressing up a poor model with complex math doesn’t make the underlying model any better)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A gut feeling for how ideologically motivated members of each field are (I’ll glance at the journals in each field and see if my BS detector goes off)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Any major replication scandals that have occurred in the field&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll weigh the existing replication attempts most heavily, so here they are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Economics&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/351/6280/1433&quot;&gt;replication project&lt;/a&gt; done by the Experimental Economics Replication Project (EERP) had a &lt;a href=&quot;https://experimentaleconreplications.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;61% replication rate&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Psychology&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2015: The “&lt;a href=&quot;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/349/6251/aac4716&quot;&gt;Reproducibility Project: Psychology&lt;/a&gt;” attempted to replicate 100 papers published in three top psychology journals in 2008. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/news/over-half-of-psychology-studies-fail-reproducibility-test-1.18248&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;39%&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;strong&gt;of papers successfully replicated).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0167487018303283#b0280&quot;&gt;The Many Labs Projects 1, 2, and 3&lt;/a&gt; performed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.replicationmarkets.com/index.php/2019/06/24/what-is-high-powered-replication/&quot;&gt;ideal,&lt;/a&gt; high-&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.replicationmarkets.com/index.php/2019/06/24/what-is-high-powered-replication/&quot;&gt;quality replications&lt;/a&gt; (i.e., multiple labs attempted to replicate findings). The replication rates were 77%, 50%, and 30%, respectively. The total replication rate (i.e., the weighted sum) was &lt;strong&gt;53%&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;other-metrics-of-epistemic-hygiene&quot;&gt;Other Metrics of Epistemic Hygiene&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;economics&quot;&gt;Economics&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Economists have been discussing replication for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nber.org/papers/w13026&quot;&gt;quite a while.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, economics is having &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/opinion/articles/2018-09-17/economics-gets-it-wrong-because-research-is-hard-to-replicate&quot;&gt;its own replication crisis&lt;/a&gt;. Consider publication bias among three of the top economics journals, for example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;wp-block-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    We observe a two-humped camel shape with missing p-values between 0.25 and 0.10 that can be retrieved just after the 0.05 threshold and represent 10-20 percent of marginally rejected tests. Our interpretation is that researchers inflate the value of just-rejected tests by choosing &amp;#8220;significant&amp;#8221; specifications.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  
  &lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ftp.iza.org/dp7268.pdf&quot;&gt;Brodeur et al., 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt; 
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/p_hacking_econ.png&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 80%; max-height: 75%; display: block; margin: 0 auto;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there weren’t publication bias, we’d expect the distribution of z-statistics to smoothly decrease, approximating the tail of a normal distribution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, certain “causal” inference methods in economics, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Difference_in_differences&quot;&gt;difference in differences&lt;/a&gt;—exploiting natural experiments in longitudinal data, e.g., the effects of a new state policy on some outcome—seem to be particularly &lt;a href=&quot;http://ftp.iza.org/dp11796.pdf&quot;&gt;prone to publication bias and p-hacking&lt;/a&gt;. Whereas, randomized controlled trials (the gold standard of causal inference) and regression discontinuity (using putatively random, exogenous treatments to mimic an RCT) don’t demonstrate the same degree of publication bias.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/z_density_econ_methods.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 80%; max-height: 75%; display: block; margin: 0 auto;&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
        The stars correspond to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Z-test&quot;&gt;z-scores&lt;/a&gt; for p-values of 0.1, 0.05, and 0.01.
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Effect sizes in economics are &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1111/ecoj.12461&quot;&gt;wildly overestimated&lt;/a&gt;, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;psychology&quot;&gt;Psychology&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m pretty sure most academics have heard about the psychology replication crisis; there’s a lot of talk about it. Given this and the fact that there have been many more replication efforts in psychology than in other fields, I’ll just stick to the empirical data for my priors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;education&quot;&gt;Education&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the exception of &lt;a href=&quot;https://adamlgreen.com/smpy/&quot;&gt;research on exceptional children&lt;/a&gt; and educational acceleration/tracking (as they’re grounded in strong psychometric foundations), most education research won’t replicate, I imagine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Per &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2014/08/14/almost-no-education-research-replicated-new-article-shows&quot;&gt;Inside Higher Ed&lt;/a&gt;, “Only 0.13 percent of education articles published in the field’s top 100 journals are replications, write Matthew Makel, a gifted-education research specialist at Duke University, and Jonathan Plucker, a professor of educational psychology and cognitive science at Indiana University. In psychology, by contrast, 1.07 percent of studies in the field’s top 100 journals are replications, a 2012 study found.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Education research also places a premium on novelty (which is what happens when you’re grasping at straws for an education intervention that produces long-lasting, positive effects):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;50%&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/zIUQK1yD95M&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With regard to specific replication failures in education research, growth mindset comes to mind (which I suppose is part of Psychology, too). Though initially hyped (TED talks and all), the most recent, largest replication studies have all flopped, demonstrating tiny effect sizes. Five days after posting a preprint of one such massive replication, the authors took the preprint down:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;
    This is extremely strong evidence that growth mindset does not have any important causal impact on academic achievement. It was a huge embarrassment for the authors, and they removed the preprint 5 days later. &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/psychology?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#psychology&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/edutwitter?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#edutwitter&lt;/a&gt; 3/
  &lt;/p&gt;— Russell T. Warne 🇺🇸🇨🇱 (@Russwarne) 
  
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Russwarne/status/1107555420636274688?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;March 18, 2019&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When pressed about the minuscule effect sizes, Dweck (the researcher who popularized mindset theory) was evasive:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;50%&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/dxsLmCNlwpk&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dweck is just a single bad-faith actor (*cough* &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.allamericanspeakers.com/speakers/9233/Carol-Dweck#:~:text=Carol%20Dweck%20is%20a%20keynote,your%20event%20is%20%2430%2C000%20%2D%20%2450%2C000.&quot;&gt;financial incentives&lt;/a&gt; *cough*) in education/psychology research; she doesn’t represent the field as a whole. But the fact that growth mindset theory has been taken seriously for this long and still won’t die suggests that education research is hostile to dissent and has bad epistemic hygiene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other educational claims that have failed, are p-hacked to death, or have inflated/overhyped effect sizes (that I can recall off the top of my head):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Flipped classrooms, which &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://seii.mit.edu/research/study/effects-of-the-flipped-classroom-evidence-from-a-randomized-trial/&quot;&gt;exacerbate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://seii.mit.edu/research/study/effects-of-the-flipped-classroom-evidence-from-a-randomized-trial/&quot;&gt;achievement gaps&lt;/a&gt; between the worst and best students&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Teacher value-added studies, which have tiny effect sizes (viz., work done by Raj Chetty, who is an economist)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Early-life educational interventions to improve academic outcomes (viz., the work of Heckmann); these interventions seem to have a positive effect on non-academic outcomes, though. That said, the literature is &lt;a href=&quot;https://rpubs.com/EmilOWK/pub_bias_early_intervention&quot;&gt;rife with publication bias&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;criminology-and-sociology&quot;&gt;Criminology and Sociology&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;wp-block-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    In criminology journals in particular, &lt;strong&gt;replication studies constitute just&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;over 2 percent of the articles&lt;/strong&gt; published between 2006 and 2010. Further, those replication studies that were published in criminology journals in that period tended to conflict with the original studies.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  
  &lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/1477370815578197?journalCode=euca&quot;&gt;&amp;#8220;Replication in criminology: A necessary practice&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know much about criminology, but apparently it does replications at twice the rate of psychology, which bodes well. However, like education research and psychology, &lt;a href=&quot;https://osf.io/qmeba/&quot;&gt;criminology has&lt;/a&gt; extolled novel interventions that ended up not replicating with similarly large effect sizes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Sociology, on the other hand, a large proportion of researchers aren’t willing to release their data (see this informal 2015 &lt;a href=&quot;https://orgtheory.wordpress.com/2015/08/11/sociologists-need-to-be-better-at-replication-a-guest-post-by-cristobal-young/&quot;&gt;study, N = 53&lt;/a&gt;), suggesting a lack of replication culture. Here’s what the sociologists &lt;a href=&quot;https://osf.io/preprints/socarxiv/5bck9/&quot;&gt;Jeremy Freese and David Peterson&lt;/a&gt; have to say:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;wp-block-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    As sociologists, the most striking thing in reviewing recent developments in social science replication is how much all our neighbors seem to be talking and doing about improving replicability. Reading economists, it is hard not to connect their relatively strict replication culture with their sense of importance: shouldn’t a field that has the ear of policy-makers do work that is available for critical inspection by others? The potential for a gloomy circle ensues, in which sociology would be more concerned with replication and transparency if it was more influential, but unwillingness to keep current on these issues prevents it from being more influential. In any case, the integrative and interdisciplinary ambitions of many sociologists are obviously hindered by the field’s inertness on these issues despite the growing sense in nearby disciplines that they are vital to ensuring research integrity.
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly, like in most social sciences, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gwern.net/docs/statistics/bias/2008-gerber.pdf&quot;&gt;we see evidence&lt;/a&gt; of publication bias:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/soc_pub_bias.png&quot; loading=&quot;lazy&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 80%; max-height: 75%; display: block; margin: 0 auto;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;political-science&quot;&gt;Political Science&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know much about political science, but it seems to have had its fair share of shoddy findings and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2015/05/26/science/maligned-study-on-gay-marriage-is-shaking-trust.htmlhttps://www.nytimes.com/2015/05/26/science/maligned-study-on-gay-marriage-is-shaking-trust.html&quot;&gt;data fabrication&lt;/a&gt;. That said, researchers have responded with &lt;a href=&quot;https://politicalsciencereplication.wordpress.com/2018/07/14/replication-and-transparency-in-political-science-did-we-make-any-progress/&quot;&gt;calls for better epistemic hygiene practices&lt;/a&gt; and journals have adjusted accordingly. There’s even an &lt;a href=&quot;https://dataverse.harvard.edu/dataverse/gov2001&quot;&gt;active page&lt;/a&gt; with replications of prominent political science papers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;management-and-marketing&quot;&gt;Management and Marketing&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Management and Marketing (M&amp;amp;M) seem to be a mix of social psychology, industrial/organizational &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apa.org/ed/graduate/specialize/industrial&quot;&gt;(IO) psych&lt;/a&gt;, and political science. For example, one of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/jpart/article/27/1/197/2629303&quot;&gt;most cited articles&lt;/a&gt; in a top M&amp;amp;M journal showcases some priming interaction effects, which is essentially something straight out psychology (that, we should note, hasn’t had the best replication record). So, we might imagine that the replication rate of M&amp;amp;M will be equal to that of psychology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, there’s not a lot of data out there on M&amp;amp;M replication. It’s clear that the field &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/14719037.2017.1282003#&quot;&gt;doesn’t talk about replication much&lt;/a&gt;, though &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s11301-018-0149-3&quot;&gt;apparently&lt;/a&gt; “&lt;em&gt;Management Review Quarterly (MRQ)&lt;/em&gt; [a top journal] publishes structured literature reviews, meta-analyses and, since 2018, replications.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My impression is that &lt;strong&gt;Replication Markets participants are systematically underpredicting the replicability of research in Management and Marketing&lt;/strong&gt;, probably because many of them are technical types allergic to business, marketing, and soft skills (even though most M&amp;amp;M papers aren’t specifically about those topics). This presents an interesting opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-replication-priors&quot;&gt;My Replication Priors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I’ll put my money where my mouth is (metaphorically, as there is no financial downside, just opportunity cost and being wrong) and provide my replication base rates:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Economics:&lt;/strong&gt; 60 ± 5%&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Psychology:&lt;/strong&gt; 55 ± 5%&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marketing and Management:&lt;/strong&gt; 50 ± 10%&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Political Science:&lt;/strong&gt; 45 ± 10%&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sociology and Criminology:&lt;/strong&gt; 45% ± 10%&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Education Research:&lt;/strong&gt; 40 ± 10% (I hope my priors aren’t too influenced by my research on the topic)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;will-replication-rates-vary-significantly-by-year&quot;&gt;Will Replication Rates Vary Significantly By Year?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One might intuit that as norms around scientific best practice change, so too will the quality of science. How could we confirm this before the replications are attempted?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A naïve approach would be to look at Google search term trends over time. For example, here are the trends for “psychology replication” and “open science” from 2004 to 2019:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/Untitled-picture.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 80%; max-height: 75%; display: block; margin: 0 auto;&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the number of publications mentioning both “psychology” and “replication”:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/dimensions_psych_final.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 80%; max-height: 75%; display: block; margin: 0 auto;&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise with &lt;a href=&quot;https://app.dimensions.ai/analytics/publication/overview/timeline?search_text=replication%20AND%20economics&amp;amp;search_type=kws&amp;amp;search_field=full_search&quot;&gt;economics&lt;/a&gt;, which has seen a similar 2x increase for publications mentioning both “economics” and “replication”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/dimensions_econ_final.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 80%; max-height: 75%; display: block; margin: 0 auto;&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trends look similar for all other social science fields being replicated in SCORE. However, these graphs show total publications over time, which increase as the fields grow larger. &lt;strong&gt;If we compare these trends to the number of publications in the fields as a whole, we see that the number of publications with the term “replication” has kept pace with the field (that is, it hasn’t accelerated).&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what we’d expect. Yes, there have been some incredibly cool developments in open science over the past five years or so, like the Open Science Framework (OSF), which takes the friction out of preregistration, public sharing of data, methods, code, and more. There have also been a few notable replication projects. Many of these things are possible thanks to the Center for Open Science (COS), which is funded by &lt;a href=&quot;https://cos.io/about/our-sponsors/&quot;&gt;Arnold Ventures, DARPA, and others.&lt;/a&gt; In 2016 the COS released new opensource preprint servers (e.g., PsyArXiv), which has coincided with increased publication of preprints (which have been available in the hard sciences &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ArXiv&quot;&gt;for nearly 30 years&lt;/a&gt;, and in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-019-00199-6&quot;&gt;biology for around 5&lt;/a&gt;.)  All of these trends have conspired to make science more open, presumably limiting publication bias, p-hacking, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stat.columbia.edu/~gelman/research/unpublished/p_hacking.pdf&quot;&gt;garden of forking paths&lt;/a&gt;, and other forms of academic malpractice and epistemic pollution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;All that said, talk is cheap. Though these trends indicate a growing awareness of replication and scientific best practices, it doesn’t guarantee that such trends have affected social scientists.&lt;/strong&gt; My subjective impression from various academic Twitter-verses is that young scientists tend to be quite excited about open science, replication, etc., whereas older, more established scientists aren’t quite as excited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question is: do these young scientists publish in the high-prestige journals that Replication Markets will investigate? Probably so, but the majority of papers are likely published by better-established, older scientists. &lt;strong&gt;I think there will be a 10-year lag before we see the quality of science increase significantly.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, no, I don’t believe replication rates will vary a lot over time. Yes, there will probably be a slight upward trend, maybe about 1-2% per year, but I imagine much more of the variation will be among fields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;forecasting-specific-claims&quot;&gt;Forecasting Specific Claims&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How should we forecast specific claims?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we wanted to be lazy (i.e., use heuristics), we’d take &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.lesswrong.com/wiki/Outside_view&quot;&gt;the outside view&lt;/a&gt; every time, meaning we’d bet the replication rate of study X would be equal to the replication rate of the field as a whole. If we have an inkling of epistemic humility, we might update this to reflect the belief of the prediction market as a whole, as prediction markets &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pnas.org/content/112/50/15343&quot;&gt;have been shown&lt;/a&gt; to be &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0167487018303283&quot;&gt;pretty good&lt;/a&gt; at predicting replication outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if we have subject-matter expertise, or are willing to do a bit of digging, we might take the inside view and update these priors accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rules-of-thumb&quot;&gt;Rules of Thumb&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Start with the replication rate for the field as a whole or, absent that, the replication rate for social science as a whole updated with our prior for the specific field.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Update on any relevant knowledge you might have, but only slightly. This is a gross simplification, but: forecasting tournaments show that &lt;strong&gt;small, incremental updates of our priors result in the best forecasts.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Be skeptical of certain methods (e.g., difference-in-differences designs in economics, as I discussed before) and statistical effects. For example, give less credence to interaction effects, as they &lt;a href=&quot;https://statmodeling.stat.columbia.edu/2018/03/15/need-16-times-sample-size-estimate-interaction-estimate-main-effect/&quot;&gt;require a much larger sample size&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;https://approachingblog.wordpress.com/2018/01/24/powering-your-interaction-2/&quot;&gt;be properly estimated&lt;/a&gt; and aren’t as likely to hold up in replication:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;wp-block-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    Interaction effects are notorious for being much easier to publish than to replicate, partly because it is easy for researchers to forget (?) how they tested many dozens of possible interactions before finding one that is statistically significant and can be presented as though it was hypothesized by the researchers all along.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  
  &lt;p&gt;
    Various things ought to heighten suspicion that a statistically significant interaction effect has a strong likelihood of not being “real.” Results that imply a plot like the one above practically scream “THIS RESULT WILL NOT REPLICATE.” There are so many ways of dividing a sample into subgroups, and there are so many variables in a typical dataset that have low correlation with an outcome, that it is inevitable that there will be all kinds of little pockets for high correlation for some subgroup just by chance.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  
  &lt;cite&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://scatter.wordpress.com/2008/08/19/lil-didactic-aside&quot;&gt; Jeremy Freese &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">What are Replication Markets?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Radical Educational Meritocracy: An Ethical and Empirical Defense</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/education-policy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Radical Educational Meritocracy: An Ethical and Empirical Defense" /><published>2019-07-01T08:36:09-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-01T08:36:09-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/education-policy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/education-policy/">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    “The natural distribution is neither just nor unjust; nor is it unjust that persons are born into society at some particular position. These are simply natural facts. What is just and unjust is the way that institutions deal with these facts.”
  &lt;/p&gt;
  
  &lt;cite&gt; &lt;em&gt;John Rawls, A Theory of Justice (1971)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The behavioral geneticist Paige Harden gave an interesting &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/kph3k/status/1110322719822737408&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/a&gt;, “A World with Equity in Educational Success.” Speaking to an audience of educators and educational policymakers, she argues that though genetic differences have historically been seen as an enemy of educational equity, our rapidly growing genetic knowledge can be used in service of educational equity and social justice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harden rightly points out that the study of heredity has historically been used to odious ends: forced sterilization, genocide, etc. She claims that these historical atrocities have been motivated by three incorrect and dangerous ideas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Genetic essentialism&lt;/em&gt;: people have an essence, a true self, that is defined by their genes. This idea is dangerous because it links our moral worth to our DNA. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Genetic determinism&lt;/em&gt;: genes determine your life outcomes. This idea is dangerous because it saps our will to create a better world. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Genetic and scientific racism&lt;/em&gt;: some races/ethnicities/populations are better than others due to innate genetic differences. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harden notes that the audience might bristle at this talk of genetics. However, this needn’t be the case: she believes there’s real potential for using genetics to establish educational equity. The upshot of her talk is that we can recast these three hereditarian ideas into the following more justifiable claims:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Genetic luck&lt;/em&gt;: though we are all dealt a different genetic hand, no one hand is more praiseworthy than another since it is all a matter of luck. No one has earned their DNA sequence.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Genetics as a tool for identifying potential for growth:&lt;/em&gt; genetics can be used to identify untapped potential and assess if schools are adequately dealing with this potential. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Prioritizing diversity in the genomics research world:&lt;/em&gt; though 79% of participants in genetic research are of European ancestry, genetics can be used to empower historically oppressed populations by involving members of these groups, both as study participants and researchers. &lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to her, in the face of the DNA revolution, we should “take the science of genetic differences and peel it away from these [three dangerous] ideas that have plagued any discussion of inherited differences for the last century and actually use the tools of modern genomics as a tool for equity.”  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I largely agree with Harden on the empirical research on genetics and educational attainment. However, I’m far more pessimistic and don’t believe genetics can or should be used to advance an equity agenda. I’ll argue that despite our best efforts, we will be unable to reconcile the &lt;a href=&quot;https://genomebiology.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s13059-018-1506-1&quot;&gt;deluge of genetic research&lt;/a&gt; coming out with goals of equity. That said, ultimately I don’t believe there’s a lot of daylight between Harden and me on this issue, other than for a few key ethical assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: This essay presumes familiarity with behavioral genetics. For a brief primer, check out &lt;a href=&quot;https://quillette.com/2018/09/25/forget-nature-versus-nurture-nature-has-won/&quot;&gt;this review&lt;/a&gt; of Robert Plomin’s book, &lt;em&gt;Blueprint&lt;/em&gt;. To make a long story short, in the past 5-10 years, due to a steep decline in the cost of genotyping (sequencing a set of genetic markers) and studies done on this genetic data, we are quickly developing genetic predictors (called polygenic scores, PGS, or PRS) of traits like educational attainment (EA). These predictors currently explain around &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/30038396&quot;&gt;13% of the variance in educational attainment&lt;/a&gt;, which is as predictive as knowing one’s parental income level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;&quot; id=&quot;steelmanning&quot;&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;steelmanning-harden-on-equity&quot;&gt;Steelmanning Harden on Equity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oecd.org/education/school/50293148.pdf&quot;&gt;OECD definition&lt;/a&gt; of educational equity that Harden cites has two components: inclusion—“ensuring that all students reach at least a basic minimum level of skills”—and fairness—“personal or socio-economic circumstances, such as gender, ethnic origin or family background are not obstacles to educational success” (p. 15). On its face, both aspects of educational equity seem laudable. We want an informed citizenry that is able to do basic math, reading and science; and we don’t want there to be personal or socio-economic impediments to educational success. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harden only briefly sketches how genetics (and her three principles) will aid her goal of educational equity. So, I’ll attempt to flesh out a charitable vision of (i.e., &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.lesswrong.com/wiki/Steel_man&quot;&gt;steelman&lt;/a&gt;) what she might have in mind: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone is dealt a genetic hand which they had no control over (&lt;em&gt;genetic luck&lt;/em&gt;). With respect to education, our hands differ in intelligence, conscientiousness, and other aspects of personality. Though twin studies pin the heritability of educational attainment in Western countries at somewhere &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/sf/article-abstract/92/1/109/2235872?redirectedFrom=fulltext&quot;&gt;between 40%&lt;/a&gt; (for total years of education) and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4210287/&quot;&gt;60%&lt;/a&gt; (for &lt;a href=&quot;https://simple.wikipedia.org/wiki/General_Certificate_of_Secondary_Education&quot;&gt;GCSE exam&lt;/a&gt; scores), and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4918078/&quot;&gt;GCTA&lt;/a&gt; pins the SNP heritability (disregarding rare variants, which aren’t included in typical SNP-chips and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/588020v1&quot;&gt;probably explain the discrepancy&lt;/a&gt; between SNP-based heritability estimates and twin study-based heritability estimates) anywhere between &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4051988/&quot;&gt;20%&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4314507/&quot;&gt;and&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0049089X19301267&quot;&gt;40%&lt;/a&gt;, there’s a lot of wiggle room left, even if much of the remaining variability is due to non-shared environment. Because of this, we may be able to address achievement gaps with better social programs that target these disparities in shared environment. Genetics will aid us in doing so, by identifying the points in development when intervention will be most useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, the SNP heritability figures might be overestimates, since &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/605006v1&quot;&gt;within-family heritability&lt;/a&gt; seems to be markedly lower than between-family heritability. This suggests the role of shared environment (including shared environmental effects that are passively correlated with additive genetic effects, called &lt;a href=&quot;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/359/6374/424&quot;&gt;“genetic nurture”&lt;/a&gt;) might be more important than previously believed. That is, the polygenic predictors from molecular genetic studies might be capturing, for example, gene-environment correlations, because those with smarter parents not only inherit their parents’ genes but the home environment their parents create. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our current, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/30038396&quot;&gt;rudimentary genetic predictors&lt;/a&gt; of educational attainment are useful at the population level, not the individual level. &lt;em&gt;On average,&lt;/em&gt; individuals with higher polygenic scores for educational attainment tend to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4946990/&quot;&gt;be more economically mobile&lt;/a&gt; regardless of childhood socioeconomic status, for example. As stated in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/biorxiv/early/2019/04/05/598532.full.pdf&quot;&gt;a paper&lt;/a&gt; Harden was co-lead author on, “Integrating genetic information in educational research also has the potential to introduce a novel source of data for researchers and policymakers interested in estimating schooling effects on the distribution of student outcomes.” For example, we might be able to use school-wide PGS heritability figures to ensure as level a playing field as possible; this will maximize the chance that all students reach the basic minimum level of skills (inclusion) and that family background won’t be an impediment to educational success (fairness). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;equality-of-outcome-and-opportunity&quot;&gt;Equality of Outcome and Opportunity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I agree with most of what I stated in my recapitulation of Harden’s views on behavioral genetic research. I hope she’d agree, too. However, our intuitions differ on how this research can and should be applied to the goal of equity. Here I’ll outline the doubts I have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The inclusion clause of the OECD definition of equity stipulates that all students reach at least a basic minimum level of skills; in other words, there must be a minimum level of equality of outcome. The fly in the ointment is that many individuals are simply not capable of meeting these basic minimum levels of skill, no matter how many resources we pour into them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, consider the work of the National Assessment of Educational Progress (NAEP), a US Department of Education project that since 1971 has been putting out The Nation’s Report Card, “the largest ongoing assessment of what U.S. students know and can do.” This report card finds that in 2017, among public school students, only 39% and 35% percent of 4th graders were at or above the NAEP Proficient level for mathematics and reading, respectively. The outlook looks equally bad if not worse for 8th and 12th graders. And the standards aren’t especially high, as &lt;a href=&quot;https://nces.ed.gov/nationsreportcard/about/booklets.aspx&quot;&gt;sample questions&lt;/a&gt; for each proficiency level (basic, proficient, and advanced) show.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But suppose we relax our criteria and look at students who are at or above the lowest of NAEP standards in math and reading, the &lt;em&gt;Basic&lt;/em&gt; level. 19%, 30%, and 40% of public school students in Grades 4, 8, and 12 fail to meet these math standards; for reading, the percentages are 32%, 25%, and 29%. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, a basic minimum of educational attainment is untenable as a benchmark for justice, or ‘equity’, unless we decrease our academic standards to accommodate a significant proportion of the student population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fairness clause of the OECD definition of equity, on the other hand, seems much more reasonable: the removal of personal and family-background obstacles. We might call it “equality of opportunity.” This seems like a desirable goal. But is it possible? Unfortunately, no. The idea of equality of opportunity is not as quixotic as the idea of equality of outcome but it is untenable nonetheless. This is for a couple of reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first reason is that &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.geneticshumanagency.org/ff/wp-content/uploads/sites/9/2017/05/FortunesFavor-05.11.2017-v2.pdf&quot;&gt;the genetic lottery&lt;/a&gt; places an upper limit on the extent to which we can achieve equality of opportunity. To quote the behavioral geneticist Robert Plomin:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;wp-block-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    &lt;em&gt;“[G]enetic inequality&amp;#8230;leads to an inherent inequality of opportunity. That is, children dealt a lucky genetic hand have a better chance of doing well at school and getting a better job and making more money. This inequality in outcome is not going to be tackled indirectly through the educational system. As mentioned, if all children were taught exactly the same, their genetic differences would still lead to differences in their achievement, which would lead to differences in occupational outcomes.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
  
  &lt;cite&gt;&lt;em&gt;Blueprint, &lt;/em&gt;Robert Plomin&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second reason true equality of opportunity is impossible is that we don’t have unlimited educational resources, so we can’t realistically give any individual all the help and time they need. At the elementary and secondary level, total US public education spending &lt;a href=&quot;https://nces.ed.gov/programs/coe/indicator_cmb.asp&quot;&gt;amounted to $700 billion&lt;/a&gt; (nearly $14,000 per student) in 2015-16. Bryan Caplan and others &lt;a href=&quot;https://press.princeton.edu/titles/11225.html&quot;&gt;have argued&lt;/a&gt; that much of this spending is bloat. Yet even if you don’t buy that argument, it seems that throwing more money at the problem won’t solve it, considering how much money is already being spent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;us-educational-reform-attempts-to-achieve-equality-of-opportunity&quot;&gt;US Educational Reform: Attempts to Achieve Equality of Opportunity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One might retort that we don’t know that equality of opportunity is impossible since we’ve never really attempted it. However, this is largely wrong. Efforts to help the worst students improve their academic performance—i.e., our best approximations of equality of opportunity—have been numerous, yet all these efforts have failed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the US, they began with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://socialwelfare.library.vcu.edu/programs/education/elementary-and-secondary-education-act-of-1965/&quot;&gt;Elementary and Secondary Education Act (ESEA)&lt;/a&gt;, signed into law by President Lyndon B. Johnson in 1965, as part of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/War_on_Poverty&quot;&gt;War on Poverty&lt;/a&gt;. Title 1 of this act disbursed money to school districts with a high proportion of disadvantaged students, in an attempt to close achievement gaps. Unfortunately, the ESEA didn’t achieve its intended effect (if it had, we likely wouldn’t be talking about equality of opportunity right now). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NAEP only began &lt;a href=&quot;https://nces.ed.gov/nationsreportcard/pdf/main1996/97985r.pdf&quot;&gt;collecting data on average mathematics test scores&lt;/a&gt; disaggregated by parent’s highest level of education in 1978, so it’s slightly difficult to determine the effect of the ESEA on the achievement gap. Fortunately, the NAEP bins the test score data into three age groups—age nine, thirteen, and seventeen—so we can look at members of the oldest bin, who would have entered elementary school in 1967, two years after the ESEA came into effect. In 1978, the difference between the average math test scores of seventeen-year-olds whose parents graduated college vs. those whose parents didn’t finish high school was 37 points, equivalent to more than a whole standard deviation difference. By 1996, the mean difference was essentially the same (p. 74-75). The data on reading scores goes all the way back to 1971, where the picture is similar (p. 125-126). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other notable wide-scale attempt to close achievement gaps was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.edweek.org/ew/section/multimedia/no-child-left-behind-overview-definition-summary.html&quot;&gt;No Child Left Behind (NCLB) Act&lt;/a&gt;, a reauthorization of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www2.ed.gov/policy/elsec/leg/esea02/pg1.html&quot;&gt;ESEA&lt;/a&gt; enacted in 2001 under President Bush. NCLB threatened and imposed sanctions against low-performing schools that didn’t demonstrate year-on-year improvements in test scores. Unfortunately, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vox.com/2015/7/27/9045491/no-child-left-behind-accountability&quot;&gt;NCLB&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/no-child-has-failed/2015/02/13/8d619026-b2f8-11e4-827f-93f454140e2b_story.html&quot;&gt;failed&lt;/a&gt;. Its impact was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nber.org/papers/w20511.pdf&quot;&gt;nil&lt;/a&gt; at worst, and small at best (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nber.org/papers/w15531.pdf&quot;&gt;though only for math scores&lt;/a&gt;). Even the US Department of Education admits that the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ed.gov/news/press-releases/fact-sheet-testing-action-plan&quot;&gt;excessive emphasis placed on standardized tests&lt;/a&gt; under NCLB had perverse effects. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t to say no progress has been made: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nationsreportcard.gov/reading_math_2017_highlights/&quot;&gt;from 1990 to 2017&lt;/a&gt;, the 4th-grade average NAEP math scores increased from the &lt;em&gt;Basic&lt;/em&gt; level to almost the &lt;em&gt;Proficient&lt;/em&gt; level. However, the average reading score has barely improved during the same period. But lest we attribute these gains to NCLB, the majority of mathematics gains were made from 1990-2003, before NCLB came into full effect. Worst of all, it seems that the highest performing students are the ones improving the most, both in reading and math, whereas the lowest-performing students’ floundering only worsens. That is, the gap between the best- and worst-performing students continues to widen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;deconstructing-the-debate&quot;&gt;Deconstructing the Debate&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though disheartening, none of these findings on the failures of educational interventions are terribly surprising given what we know about the behavioral genetics of educational attainment and intelligence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, even if many of the premises of the OECD definition of equity are demonstrably false, equality of opportunity still seems like a worthy goal. For even if educational resources are scarce and true equality of opportunity is impossible, we should try to minimize the unfairness we have control over by allocating educational resources most effectively. And even if the ESEA and NCLB failed to improve the average test scores of the disadvantaged, this doesn’t mean these policies didn’t aid precocious children on the margins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an ideal world, we’d have equality of opportunity &lt;a href=&quot;https://english.stackexchange.com/questions/70018/meaning-of-modulo-the-fact&quot;&gt;modulo&lt;/a&gt; genetic inequality: the bright kid would get the resources he or she needs, irrespective of his or her parents’ income. The crux of the disagreement between Harden and me is how this should be done and what we’re willing to do it at the expense of. In other words, what sorts of tradeoffs do we want to make, and at what point have we gone too far trying to create an equality of outcome?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Genetics research and the history of educational interventions considerably constrain the space of reasonable answers to these questions. That said, there’s still room for difference of opinion on the empirical and ethical assumptions underlying our answers to these questions. Here I’ll lay out the substantive dimensions along which these assumptions can differ.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;empirical-dimensions-to-disagree-on&quot;&gt;Empirical Dimensions To Disagree On &lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Human Capital Development&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How much of education is about developing real human capital and how much is merely &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/qje/article-lookup/doi/10.2307/1882010&quot;&gt;signaling&lt;/a&gt;? How large are the &lt;a href=&quot;https://philpapers.org/archive/ANOPGA-5.pdf&quot;&gt;positive externalities from education&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Utility and&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tractability of Broad, Scalable Educational Intervention&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is variation in educational attainment due mostly to genetic variation, shared environmental variation, or non-shared environmental variation? Given our answer to this question, how useful/tractable do we believe educational interventions will be? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we are able to improve educational outcomes, are these improvements psychometrically valid? That is, are we merely teaching to the test or are we actually improving intelligence? (Is this even an important question to be asking?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At what point do we reach diminishing returns to education? What constitutes utility, the dependent variable, in this analysis?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does there exist some unknown educational intervention that reliably improves educational outcomes and/or intelligence? Will &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brookings.edu/research/why-federal-spending-on-disadvantaged-students-title-i-doesnt-work/&quot;&gt;throwing money at the problem&lt;/a&gt; make things better or are the prospects truly as grim as they seem?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Utility and Tractability of Educational Acceleration for Bright Students&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How well does educational acceleration work? Is education particularly useful for kids on the far right of the ability distribution? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Will Fixing Education Cure Underlying Inequality&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you believe in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2019/07/education-isnt-enough/590611/&quot;&gt;“educationism”&lt;/a&gt;—the idea that social inequality is due to differential access to education—or do you believe the problem runs deeper?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How Pressing is the Problem of Automation? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are “&lt;a href=&quot;https://irs.princeton.edu/sites/irs/files/event/uploads/robots_and_jobs_march_3.17.2017_final.pdf&quot;&gt;robots really taking our jobs&lt;/a&gt;” and is &lt;a href=&quot;https://a16z.com/2011/08/20/why-software-is-eating-the-world/&quot;&gt;“software eating the world”&lt;/a&gt;? Is this trend going to accelerate? Will this trend disproportionately affect those with little education and prospects of retraining for a new job?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ethical-dimensions-to-disagree-on&quot;&gt;Ethical Dimensions to Disagree On&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Discounting Rate of Future Lives&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should we prioritize economic growth and improvements in quality of life for all over short-term inequality; i.e., how heavily do we discount the value of future human lives? (This is a question of population ethics.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ethical Values&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is fairness/justice more important than average well-being?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Value of Education&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is education merely an instrumental good or does it have inherent value (e.g., moral edification, intellectual fulfillment, etc.)?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will education be able to prepare students for the jobs of tomorrow? Do we even know what those jobs will be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Educational Austerity&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How much should we cut the educational budget? Where do we situate education in our list of priorities?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;three-visions-for-k-12-public-education&quot;&gt;Three Visions for K-12 Public Education&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I situate three visions—two commonly held and one novel—along the dimensions I’ve outlined. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-egalitarian-vision&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Egalitarian Vision&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s get unrealistic views off the table. Many people, who are unaware of behavioral genetics research, believe some element of what we can call “the egalitarian vision.” This vision states that, on the empirical front, intelligence is completely malleable and the achievement gap will be closed if we use enough educational resources, and, on the ethical front, that we should attempt to redress educational inequality at all costs. Charles Murray called this ideology “educational romanticism…The lie is that every child can be anything he or she wants to be” (&lt;em&gt;Real Education&lt;/em&gt;, p. 11). Anyone who proffers these sorts of views is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jgRU67lwsI4&quot;&gt;ideological suicide bomber being invited to dinner&lt;/a&gt;: they don’t deserve a place at the table because they won’t engage with the empirical evidence, stifling fruitful conversation. So, we needn’t give this scheme any more thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-rawlsian-vision-and-noble-lies&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Rawlsian Vision and Noble Lies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I’ll call the “Rawlsian vision” attempts to reconcile egalitarian ethics with realism about behavioral genetics. One might also call this &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Luck_egalitarianism&quot;&gt;luck egalitarianism&lt;/a&gt;. According to luck egalitarianism, we should create institutions that strive to minimize opportunities and power that come from undeserved advantages, such as genetic endowment or other happenstance of birth (like being born in a first-world country). Per Rawls, this type of &lt;a href=&quot;https://eportfolios.macaulay.cuny.edu/thorne15/files/2015/03/Rawls-JUSTICE-AS-FAIRNESS.pdf&quot;&gt;fairness&lt;/a&gt; constitutes a just world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where &lt;a href=&quot;https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/rawls/#TwoPriJusFai&quot;&gt;Rawls’ theory of justice&lt;/a&gt; becomes interesting is in its second principle, the principle concerning social and economic inequalities. The first part of this principle—that people of equal ability should have the same educational and economic opportunities—takes into account varying genetic endowments and makes good sense. However, the second part of this principle, the difference principle, which states that social and economic inequalities must be of greatest benefit to the most disadvantaged members of society, smuggles in certain normative assumptions: namely, that we ought to minimize inequality at the expense of other values, such as maximizing total utility. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.geneticshumanagency.org/ff/wp-content/uploads/sites/9/2017/05/FortunesFavor-05.11.2017-v2.pdf&quot;&gt;ascribe&lt;/a&gt; the Rawlsian vision to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.geneticshumanagency.org/ff/wp-content/uploads/sites/9/2017/05/FortunesFavor-05.11.2017-v2.pdf&quot;&gt;Paige Harden&lt;/a&gt;. Robert Plomin seems to subscribe to this sort of view, too, though he seems to believe genetics play a stronger role than Harden does, asserting that education won’t address inherent inequality of opportunity:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;wp-block-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    “My value system suggests that we need to replace meritocracy with a just society&amp;#8230;economic inequality could be dealt with directly through a redistributive tax system that reduces the gap between rich and poor.”
  &lt;/p&gt;
  
  &lt;cite&gt;&lt;em&gt;Blueprint, &lt;/em&gt;Robert Plomin&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this excerpt of &lt;em&gt;Blueprint&lt;/em&gt;, Plomin doesn’t flesh out what sort of policy prescriptions follow from genetics “because policies depend on values.” His one interesting idea on this front is that “instead of genetics being antithetical to equal opportunity, heritability of outcomes can be seen as an index of equality of opportunity.” I agree wholeheartedly with this idea and will get to its implementation later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in Plomin’s earlier book on genetics and education, which he co-authored with Kathryn Asbury, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Genes-Impact-Genetics-Education-Achievement/dp/1118482816&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;G is for Genes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, he offers some rather anodyne policy suggestions such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;wp-block-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    Offer free, high-quality preschool education to disadvantaged children from age 2, free, high-quality preschool education to all children from age 3 to 4, and extra support to children in low-SES families from birth.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  
  &lt;cite&gt;&lt;em&gt;G is for Genes&lt;/em&gt;, Kathryn Asbury and Robert Plomin (p. 170)&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, preschool interventions like Headstart seem to have no &lt;em&gt;lasting&lt;/em&gt; impact on cognitive abilities (as measured by test scores) and only a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nber.org/papers/w21766.pdf&quot;&gt;small positive impact on non-cognitive abilities&lt;/a&gt; like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.umass.edu/preferen/You%20Must%20Read%20This/HeckmanAER2013.pdf&quot;&gt;social skills, self-control and educational attainment&lt;/a&gt;, though &lt;a href=&quot;https://rpubs.com/EmilOWK/pub_bias_early_intervention&quot;&gt;meta-analysis&lt;/a&gt; suggests &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aeaweb.org/articles?id=10.1257/jep.27.2.109&quot;&gt;publication bias in the literature&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“However,” Plomin says, “a focus on developing a growth mindset, IQ, social, and thinking skills, and self confidence, would seem to be a good idea” (170). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These ideas don’t hold water, either. Though the effects of growth mindset are &lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2015/04/08/no-clarity-around-growth-mindset-yet/&quot;&gt;mixed in studies of children and adolescents&lt;/a&gt;, they tend &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/0956797617739704&quot;&gt;to be small&lt;/a&gt;. In a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0191886917303835?via%3Dihub&quot;&gt;large sample of university students&lt;/a&gt;, growth mindset wasn’t significantly related to scholastic aptitude. In a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gwern.net/docs/psychology/writing/2017-dobronyi.pdf&quot;&gt;randomized control trial of a goal-setting intervention&lt;/a&gt; for first-year undergraduates, the treatment had no effect on GPA, course credits, or second-year persistence. And the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Russwarne/status/1152857938337210369&quot;&gt;most recent replication attempt of growth mindset training flopped spectacularly.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clearly, Plomin understands behavior genetics; as he has been working on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Twins_Early_Development_Study&quot;&gt;Twins’ Early Development Study&lt;/a&gt; for 25 years. Yet, for whatever reason, he chooses to tell &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Noble_lie&quot;&gt;noble lies&lt;/a&gt; (or, in the case of &lt;em&gt;Blueprint&lt;/em&gt;, chooses to stay silent about the policy implications of his research). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;radical-meritocracy-a-pessimistic-utilitarian-care--and-fairness-insensitive-take-on-education&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Radical Meritocracy: A Pessimistic, Utilitarian, Care- and Fairness-Insensitive Take on Education&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;wp-block-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    &lt;em&gt;The responsibility for the creation of new scientific knowledge—and for most of its application—rests on that small body of men and women who understand the fundamental laws of nature and are skilled in the techniques of scientific research. We shall have rapid or slow advance on any scientific frontier depending on the number of highly qualified and trained scientists exploring it.&amp;nbsp;&lt;/em&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;
  
  &lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nsf.gov/od/lpa/nsf50/vbush1945.htm&quot;&gt;Vannevar Bush&lt;/a&gt;, Director of the Office of Scientific Research and Development, July 1945&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I’ll make a case for the empirical and ethical premises I believe are justified and what the best possible education system would look like given these premises. In his 2008 book &lt;em&gt;Real Education&lt;/em&gt;, Charles Murray outlines “Four Simple Truths” which are wholly consistent with my argument (p. 12-13):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ability varies.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Half of the children are below average.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Too many people are going to college.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;America’s future depends on how we educate the academically gifted.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope to both build on Murray’s claims and root them in deeper ethical and empirical foundations, paying particular attention to the fourth claim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll call this system radical educational meritocracy (which I’ll henceforth refer to as “radical meritocracy”). The term meritocracy was coined by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/politics/2001/jun/29/comment&quot;&gt;Michael Young&lt;/a&gt; in his 1958 science-fiction satire, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Rise_of_the_Meritocracy&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Rise of the Meritocracy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Many consider the book’s vision to be that of a dystopia, demonstrating the folly of an administrative state’s attempt to use intelligence testing to optimize collective performance. However, if radical meritocracy were executed properly, something which is becoming more feasible, I believe it would maximize collective utility over the long-run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;motivations-underlying-radical-meritocracy&quot;&gt;Motivations Underlying Radical Meritocracy&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Radical meritocracy is motivated by a sense of urgency about the following two trends:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The increasing &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.media.mit.edu/publications/toward-understanding-the-impact-of-artificial-intelligence-on-labor/&quot;&gt;threat of automation&lt;/a&gt; and attendant &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.econ.yale.edu/smith/econ116a/keynes1.pdf&quot;&gt;“technological unemployment&lt;/a&gt;,” a term Keynes coined nearly 90 years ago. &lt;a href=&quot;https://adamlgreen.com/future/&quot;&gt;Automation will likely obsolesce&lt;/a&gt; a substantial portion of our workforce in the coming decades, deepening the economic and social fissures between the highly educated and everyone else, causing massive social disaffection.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Growing &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.existential-risk.org/concept.pdf&quot;&gt;existential risks to humanity&lt;/a&gt;, which are magnified every year by our increasing technological capabilities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I’ll quickly address why we should feel a sense of urgency about these two issues:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Automation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though the U.S. unemployment rate is at a record low, 3.6%, the labor force participation rate has been &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bls.gov/charts/employment-situation/civilian-labor-force-participation-rate.htm&quot;&gt;steadily declining since the mid to late 90’s&lt;/a&gt;. From 1979-2007, &lt;a href=&quot;https://economics.mit.edu/files/5554&quot;&gt;employment rates fell most&lt;/a&gt; for males who dropped out of or only graduated from high school. And though we’re currently in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.economist.com/leaders/2019/05/23/the-rich-world-is-enjoying-an-unprecedented-jobs-boom&quot;&gt;midst of a jobs boom&lt;/a&gt;, one in which &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.economist.com/united-states/2019/05/16/american-life-is-improving-for-the-lowest-paid&quot;&gt;weekly nominal earnings&lt;/a&gt; have been increasing for the lowest earners, many of the jobs being created are low-skill or temporary jobs (which &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/available-jobs-in-u-s-edge-higher-in-october-1544457618&quot;&gt;few people want to do&lt;/a&gt;). The prospects of job reskilling programs &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/1045159518818407&quot;&gt;are dismal&lt;/a&gt;—so it seems the truckers and journalists won’t “learn to code” any time soon—and for the majority of workers, automation has become more a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brookings.edu/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/1_autorsalomons.pdf&quot;&gt;force of labor displacement than of labor augmentation&lt;/a&gt;. Whatever the cause of these trends, the low-skilled, poorly educated worker is taking the brunt of it, and a substantial proportion of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mckinsey.com/featured-insights/future-of-work/jobs-lost-jobs-gained-what-the-future-of-work-will-mean-for-jobs-skills-and-wages#part1&quot;&gt;white-collar workers&lt;/a&gt; might soon be as well. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brookings.edu/blog/social-mobility-memos/2013/10/15/not-afraid-of-tyler-cowen-you-will-be-a-review-of-average-is-over-powering-america-beyond-the-age-of-the-great-stagnation/&quot;&gt;Average will soon be over&lt;/a&gt;. That said, it bodes well for those who perform &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/qje/article-abstract/118/4/1279/1925105&quot;&gt;cognitive, non-routine work&lt;/a&gt; and skilled &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moravec%27s_paradox&quot;&gt;manual&lt;/a&gt; trades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Existential Risk&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a variety of reasons—the existence of the Fermi Paradox, our close brushes with nuclear war in the second half of the 20th century, the ease with which bad actors can now develop dangerous bioweapons, etc.—we should be worried about existential risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relationship between humanity’s technological capabilities and our risk of extinction is probably close to an inverted U-shape. We are on the left-hand part of the curve and quickly nearing the peak, where existential risk is highest; thus, getting over the peak and reducing existential risk should be a priority, provided we care about the possible lives of our future descendants. Leopold Aschenbrenner explains this well in his paper &lt;a href=&quot;https://leopoldaschenbrenner.github.io/xriskandgrowth/ExistentialRiskAndGrowth050.pdf&quot;&gt;“Existential Risk and Growth”&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;wp-block-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    In a model of endogenous and directed technical change, with moderate parameters, existential risk follows a Kuznets-style inverted U-shape. &lt;strong&gt;This suggests we could be living in a unique “time of perils,” having developed technologies advanced enough to threaten our permanent destruction, but not having grown wealthy enough yet to be willing to spend much on safety. Accelerating growth during this “time of perils” initially increases risk, but improves the chances of humanity’s survival in the long run. &lt;/strong&gt;Conversely, even short-term stagnation could substantially curtail the future of humanity.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  
  &lt;cite&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://leopoldaschenbrenner.github.io/xriskandgrowth/ExistentialRiskAndGrowth050.pdf&quot;&gt;Leopold Aschenbrenner &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way we get over the peak of the existential risk curve is by developing better institutions and technologies. Doing this requires nurturing innovative, highly intelligent individuals who will build such technologies and institutions. Our and our descendants’ future depends on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we don’t build these technologies and institutions that allow us to crest the hill and reduce the ambient level of existential risk, given a long enough time horizon it seems the only alternative outcomes are stagnation (which is unlikely given our expanding technological capacities) or annihilation (i.e., we are hit with an existential risk which either wipes out humanity or reverts us back to an earlier technological age). Neither of these outcomes is desirable, especially the latter, so we should highly value getting over the hump of the existential risk curve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;empirical-and-ethical-premises&quot;&gt;Empirical and Ethical Premises&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the empirical front, my other premises are: education is a zero-sum, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Positional_good&quot;&gt;positional good&lt;/a&gt; mostly &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aei.org/publication/the-case-against-education-a-long-read-qa-with-bryan-caplan/&quot;&gt;about signaling and selection&lt;/a&gt;, not the development of real human capital; that said, educational interventions (like talent identification programs) are particularly useful for children on the far right end of the ability distribution, as these children go on to &lt;a href=&quot;https://adamlgreen.com/smpy/&quot;&gt;achieve disproportionate creative and professional success&lt;/a&gt; compared to their peers; for the majority of students, after teaching basic skills, we quickly reach diminishing marginal returns to education; variation in educational attainment is mostly, though certainly not completely, &lt;a href=&quot;https://psycnet.apa.org/record/2008-18777-001?mod=article_inline&quot;&gt;caused by genetic variation, not variation in access to educational resources&lt;/a&gt;; given the behavioral genetic research and the repeated failure of educational interventions to demonstrate long-term, reliable improvements in educational outcomes, it’s most parsimonious to think we’ll never discover a scalable intervention that fully closes achievement gaps between the best and worst students; finally, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2019/07/education-isnt-enough/590611/&quot;&gt;educationism&lt;/a&gt; is wrong—the relationship between education and social inequality is largely &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4946990/&quot;&gt;moderated by genetic variation&lt;/a&gt; in traits that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nber.org/papers/w25114&quot;&gt;predispose one towards economic mobility&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; family background privilege.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the ethical front, my premises are: we assume an indirect version of &lt;a href=&quot;https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/consequentialism/&quot;&gt;consequentialism&lt;/a&gt;, which means that we assume we should create institutions that tend to maximize social welfare over the long-run; we ought to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stafforini.com/docs/Cowen%20&amp;amp;%20Parfit%20-%20Against%20the%20social%20discount%20rate.pdf&quot;&gt;only minimally discount future lives&lt;/a&gt; and therefore should radically expand the temporal scope of our thinking; this means that we should &lt;a href=&quot;https://quillette.com/2018/11/21/stubborn-attachments-a-review/&quot;&gt;prioritize economic growth&lt;/a&gt; over short-term inequality, because this increases technological development, getting us over the peak of the technological-development/existential risk curve; this strategy maximizes the likelihood our species reaches the 22nd century &lt;a href=&quot;https://nickbostrom.com/astronomical/waste.html&quot;&gt;and that our descendants exist at all&lt;/a&gt;; finally, education is an instrumental good, one which most people are unable to make use of, not an intrinsic good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fully fleshing out all of these premises is beyond the scope of this essay. Nonetheless, given these premises, contra Plomin and Harden, I believe we should embrace radical meritocracy even at the expense of short-term inequality and injustice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-is-radical-meritocracy&quot;&gt;What is Radical Meritocracy?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Radical meritocracy takes on board the Rawlsian idea that we should make choices about social systems (such as what constitutes educational equality of opportunity) as if we were behind a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Veil_of_ignorance&quot;&gt;veil of ignorance&lt;/a&gt;, not knowing where we’d end up. But behind the veil, radical meritocracy permits greater variance in life outcomes if it means that total utility is higher, which flies in the face of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/rawls/#TwoPriJusFai&quot;&gt;difference principle of Rawls’ second principle of justice&lt;/a&gt;. Radical meritocracy also takes the long-term view, considering the utility of those currently alive and of our yet-to-be-born descendants (that is, it is not a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Person-affecting_view&quot;&gt;person-affecting view&lt;/a&gt;), meaning that behind the veil of ignorance one doesn’t know if they’ll be born in the 21st century or will be one of our (possibly existent) descendants living in the 31st century, colonizing the galaxy. This requires rejecting the luck egalitarians’ preoccupation with short-term inequality in favor of focusing on long-term gains in quality of life for all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;radical-meritocracy-in-practice&quot;&gt;Radical Meritocracy in Practice&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under our current K-12 system, a child’s access to educational resources is largely a matter of chance, and not correlated with their innate ability. Poor, smart kids tend to end up in the low-quality public schools near their house. Rich kids more often get sent to private schools, even if they’re a bit dull. Yes, highly &lt;a href=&quot;https://quillette.com/2019/04/03/what-new-yorks-public-schools-could-learn-from-stuyvesant/&quot;&gt;competitive specialized schools&lt;/a&gt; like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bronx_High_School_of_Science&quot;&gt;Bronx High School of Science&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stuyvesant_High_School&quot;&gt;Stuyvesant High School&lt;/a&gt; (both of which are more selective than Harvard, accepting 3% of applicants each) allow the poor but bright kids to get ahead. But these schools are currently few and far between. Under a system of radical meritocracy, there would be many more such competitive specialized schools. However, this is just the tip of the iceberg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Highly competitive public schools like Bronx Science and Stuyvesant work because they ruthlessly select for intelligence via standardized tests. The key question is if we can identify intelligence (and other elements of academic potential like creativity, curiosity, etc.) before high school. This is a signal detection problem and one of the two focuses of radical meritocracy. We’d like to nurture those rare students who have the potential to make a massive positive impact, but first, we must find them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way would be to use age 13 test scores on the SAT, as is done in talent search programs like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://my.vanderbilt.edu/smpy/&quot;&gt;Study of Mathematically Precocious Youth&lt;/a&gt; (SMPY) and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://tip.duke.edu/&quot;&gt;Duke Talent Identification Program&lt;/a&gt; (TIP). I’ll expand on this later. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Polygenic scores present another way of identifying these rare students. Though it might seem like something out of the movie &lt;em&gt;Gattaca&lt;/em&gt;, the heritability of intelligence is low during childhood and &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/1745691615617439&quot;&gt;slowly increases till peaking&lt;/a&gt; in late adolescence, so it’s conceivable that we may be able to use polygenic scores (PGS) early in life when PGS are more predictive of future educational attainment than noisy test scores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a massive caveat, though: these &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/645218v1&quot;&gt;PGS aren’t currently useful at the individual level&lt;/a&gt;, as they have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6522355/&quot;&gt;little to no&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Incremental_validity&quot;&gt;incremental validity&lt;/a&gt; over knowledge of a student’s prior educational attainment and little precision at the individual level. Additionally, some of the signal the PGS picks up on is in fact noise—&lt;a href=&quot;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/359/6374/424&quot;&gt;indirect parental effects on the phenotype of interest&lt;/a&gt;—meaning that the PGS is partly confounded by environmental effects. However, given the SNP heritability values derived from GCTA (which estimates the theoretical maximum variance our PGS could capture) and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3751588/&quot;&gt;the&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/mp2016107?fbclid=IwAR2Hv8EpgxY9iZiSFebneX4OfM6zXoRUGAHnflmkUqdfxZaGHdGWEf9dAH8&quot;&gt;rate of&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41380-019-0394-4&quot;&gt;increase&lt;/a&gt; in the variance captured by PGSs, someday we might be able to use them to identify positive outliers. If this were possible, such PGS could be used to identify children with academic potential and place them in gifted programs, for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second focus of radical meritocracy, after detecting talent, is matching it with the resources it needs. In other words, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gwern.net/docs/iq/smpy/2009-wai-2.pdf&quot;&gt;we need to&lt;/a&gt; “merge an individual’s &lt;em&gt;potential&lt;/em&gt; (abilities) and &lt;em&gt;passion&lt;/em&gt; (preferences) with educational experiences tailored to each student’s unique &lt;em&gt;promise&lt;/em&gt; (readiness to learn).” The key question in this domain is if schools and talent identification programs have a large, causal impact on student achievement. If they do not—that is, if their achievement is merely due to selection effects—then placing so much emphasis on acceleration programs is misguided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The findings on the value added by elite schools are mixed. &lt;a href=&quot;https://economics.mit.edu/files/9518&quot;&gt;Some papers&lt;/a&gt; suggest that the higher average achievement in elite schools is due to selection effects, not the school itself. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0927537116000063&quot;&gt;Other papers&lt;/a&gt; argue that school quality significantly impacts student achievement. The findings on various forms of tracking are mixed, too; for example, one study on full-grade acceleration (i.e., grade-skipping) only found a small to moderate impact on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0022440517300791#bb0125&quot;&gt;earnings&lt;/a&gt;, as compared to ability-matched, non-accelerated students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the findings on talent identification and acceleration programs like SMPY and TIP are much clearer. Such programs identify extremely precocious children and provide them with the academic stimulus and support that’s appropriate for their abilities and interests. These students go on to &lt;a href=&quot;https://adamlgreen.com/smpy/&quot;&gt;achieve above and beyond their peers&lt;/a&gt;. Even among these gifted children, increases in &lt;a href=&quot;https://pdfs.semanticscholar.org/1105/167599ed8a1fe800f1039a858073fe7e7edb.pdf&quot;&gt;intelligence produces non-linear returns&lt;/a&gt; in creative and professional achievement (i.e., intelligence keeps on giving). Most interestingly, &lt;a href=&quot;https://files.nwesd.org/website/Teaching_Learning/HiCap/2015-16%20meetings/NationEmpowered%20Vol1.pdf&quot;&gt;accelerative programs&lt;/a&gt; like SMPY and TIP have demonstrated &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/abs/10.1177/0016986210383155?journalCode=gcqb&quot;&gt;small&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.sagepub.com/stoken/default+domain/v8yScpxvaXuUk2y9Z5X9/full&quot;&gt;large&lt;/a&gt; causal effects on academic achievement, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ctd.northwestern.edu/sites/default/files/Academic%20Acceleration%20for%20Gifted%20Minority%20Students.pdf&quot;&gt;including among minority students.&lt;/a&gt; For example, as compared to non-accelerated matched control students, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gwern.net/docs/iq/smpy/2014-wai-2.pdf&quot;&gt;SMPY participants who skipped a grade&lt;/a&gt; earned twice as many STEM PhDs, produced 55% more stem publications on average and earned over 50% more doctorates. Other talent identification acceleration interventions show similar results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We shouldn’t be surprised by the SMPY and TIP findings on IQ and creative achievement. IQ is strongly linked &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/qje/article-abstract/134/2/647/5218522?redirectedFrom=fulltext&quot;&gt;to the probability of being an inventor&lt;/a&gt;, even after controlling for parental income. That said, parental income seems to have an effect on the probability of becoming an inventor, even after partialling out the effects of IQ, suggesting there exist &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/qje/article-abstract/134/2/647/5218522?redirectedFrom=fulltext&quot;&gt;“lost Einsteins”&lt;/a&gt; that we need to identify. This is the point of radical meritocracy: to identify and nurture these precocious yet underserved children, as doing so will maximize aggregate welfare. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One may still have doubts about testing, though. For example, consider &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Campbell%27s_law&quot;&gt;Campbell’s Law&lt;/a&gt;: “The more any quantitative social indicator is used for social decision-making, the more subject it will be to corruption pressures and the more apt it will be to distort and corrupt the social processes it is intended to monitor.” Campbell’s Law manifested itself during the Bush administration in increased time spent on standardized testing in public schools that faced sanctions due to No Child Left Behind. When a school district’s livelihood depends on improving test scores, they’re going to spend a lot of time prepping for them. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One might also fear that increasing the role of test scores in education might lead to a hyper-competitive educational system, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2014/08/02/opinion/sunday/south-koreas-education-system-hurts-students.html&quot;&gt;like that in South Korea&lt;/a&gt;, one in which students study for dozens of hours per week. However, I believe these fears are misplaced. The reason why talent identification programs have been so successful is that students don’t study for the SAT as twelve- and thirteen-year-olds. Yet even if they did, &lt;a href=&quot;https://hepgjournals.org/doi/abs/10.17763/haer.53.1.n06j5h5356217648&quot;&gt;meta-analysis&lt;/a&gt; and other &lt;a href=&quot;https://files.eric.ed.gov/fulltext/ED593130.pdf&quot;&gt;studies&lt;/a&gt; suggest the gains on test scores to be had from studying, at least among those ages seventeen to eighteen, are quite small. Because the test is hard to game, it’s a good indicator, one resistant to Campbell’s law. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Navigating the Tradeoff Landscape&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a cost-benefit perspective, one important detail is how our &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Detection_theory&quot;&gt;signal detection devices&lt;/a&gt; (test scores, PGS, etc.) should be calibrated; for example, how many true geniuses are we willing to miss (false negatives) in order to maximize the number of educational resources given to bright kids? Obviously, children don’t fit into the binary of bright or dull—academic potential falls along a continuum—but it’s a useful toy model for thinking of how to allocate scarce resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose we have 1000 units of educational resources and 1000 students to educate. If we could reliably identify outliers on the far right tail on the ability distribution—whether via standardized testing or PGS—would we be justified in giving them more than 1 unit of resources, thus taking away from other students? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the goal of our radical meritocracy is to maximize innovation in order to improve quality of life for all, and if you buy my premise that the marginal utility of education is substantially higher for the bright child than for the dull child—because there is a threshold effect for innovation; because children who do poorly in school tend to not like school anyway; and because improving test scores among poorly performing students has proven incredibly difficult—then it makes sense to spend these limited resources on the brighter children rather than the laggards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m certainly not claiming we ought to cut all education spending on students in the X-th percentile of intelligence and below. I’m merely stating that a more optimal allocation of education spending is possible, and we’ll get the most bang for our buck (in terms of technological innovation and long-term improvement in our collective quality of life) by focusing our efforts on the extremely smart kids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might be asking yourself: what do we do with the overwhelming majority of students who aren’t selected into a talent identification program or a highly selective, specialized high school? I’ll leave this one to Plomin and Asbury:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;wp-block-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    Increase the number and range of options available for work- and college-based vocational training; make apprenticeships more affordable for and attractive to employers, and educate pupils so they have mastered basic skills, found their true interests, and are more attractive to employers.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  
  &lt;cite&gt;&lt;em&gt;G is for Genes&lt;/em&gt;, Kathryn Asbury and Robert Plomin (p. 174)&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Germany, for example, nearly &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cleanenergywire.org/factsheets/how-germanys-vocational-education-and-training-system-works&quot;&gt;⅓ of students&lt;/a&gt; pursue vocational training. Beyond vocational training, though, I think a radical reduction in public education spending and a renewed focus on reading, writing, and arithmetic (plus increased focus on other important topics, such as how to be in a relationship, basic Western history, etc.) would be the best course of action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dimensionality-reduction-of-intuitions-around-radical-meritocracy&quot;&gt;Dimensionality Reduction of Intuitions Around Radical Meritocracy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My radical meritocracy scheme is lacking in specifics and leaves many questions unanswered. There are many topics to touch on: school choice (vouchers vs. public), how K-12 education relates to higher education (and the pernicious signal inflation that is occurring), how to change pedagogy, what to do about all the bright “learning-disabled” children that fall through the cracks of our educational system, what to do with the students not on the right tail of the ability distribution, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might react to my vision of radical meritocracy with disgust. You might find it callous. This is understandable. It’s a highly counterintuitive suggestion, predicated on ethical assumptions that we did not evolve to intuit easily (viz. utilitarianism—as opposed to thinking in terms of fairness—and extreme counterfactual and long-term thinking—as opposed to thinking parochially and falling prey to status quo bias).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you needn’t agree with my scheme; there exists a range of reasonable views between the Rawlsian take and radical meritocracy, depending on one’s opinions about the aforementioned empirical and ethical assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I bet that beliefs about each of these assumptions aren’t orthogonal. In fact, I imagine there’s quite a strong coupling among these dimensions, and knowing one’s opinion on one will allow us to reliably predict their opinions on others. This is because people’s beliefs on any issue typically aren’t motivated by pure reasoning; rather, most people arrive at their beliefs via intuitions and &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; justify them with post hoc reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If these dimensions are highly coupled, then we should be able to reduce them to fewer dimensions. Jonathan Haidt’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://moralfoundations.org/&quot;&gt;Moral Foundations Theory&lt;/a&gt; provides a potential means of doing this dimensionality reduction. I believe the primary ethical dimension— the first principal component or factor of these intuitions, so to speak—correlates strongly with the care vs. harm and fairness vs. cheating moral foundations. Individuals high in this care and fairness factor tend to favor an ethical framework that emphasizes fairness and equality; believe education is not just an instrumental good, but a good in and of itself; and are optimistic about the malleability of intelligence and our ability to improve educational outcomes. These folks, whom others have called “&lt;a href=&quot;https://quillette.com/2018/02/07/equalitarianism-progressive-bias/&quot;&gt;equalitarians&lt;/a&gt;,” likely &lt;a href=&quot;https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=3175680&quot;&gt;skew politically left.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conversely, the “utilitarian realists” (which include the radical meritocrats) are low in this care and fairness factor; believe we should not heavily discount future lives; are willing to unequally distribute educational resources based on ability, if it means that it will improve economic growth; and are skeptical of educational interventions working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever your ethical and empirical beliefs, it seems any education system rooted in the best information from behavioral genetics involves trading one form of inequality—that of &lt;a href=&quot;https://quillette.com/2019/03/13/standardized-testing-and-meritocracy/&quot;&gt;family background&lt;/a&gt;—for another—genetic inequality, or inequality in the ability to develop skills the job market will find valuable. Under radical meritocracy, we do so to maximize collective utility and the probability that our species survives through the 22nd century (and does so with ever-increasing quality of life). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Radical meritocracy isn’t fair, in the traditional sense. But it’s fair (and, in my opinion, desirable) because it generates positive externalities by matching smart kids with resources, which increases the potential for innovation and economic growth, benefiting humanity as a whole in the long-term. Perhaps counterintuitively, radical meritocracy is very &lt;a href=&quot;https://eportfolios.macaulay.cuny.edu/thorne15/files/2015/03/Rawls-JUSTICE-AS-FAIRNESS.pdf&quot;&gt;Rawlsian&lt;/a&gt; in this respect:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;wp-block-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    All social values—liberty and opportunity, income and wealth, and the bases of self-respect—are to be distributed equally unless an unequal distribution of any, or all, of these values is to everyone&amp;#8217;s advantage.
  &lt;/p&gt;
  
  &lt;cite&gt;&lt;em&gt;Justice as Fairness&lt;/em&gt;, John Rawls (p. 9)&lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But why not maintain the educational status quo? Philosopher Evan Williams &lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10677-015-9567-7&quot;&gt;has suggested&lt;/a&gt; that we may currently be engaged in various moral catastrophes that we’re completely unaware of; education may be one such catastrophe. A potential solution, per Williams, is “refocusing our educational system on identifying the most talented children and nurturing them to their full potential, not on trying to shepherd every last mediocre student into a four-year college” (9). If we truly care about the long-term future of humanity and believe that technological innovation is the means of achieving such a future, then we ought to take this idea seriously. Forestalling scientific progress (and the development of better human institutions) &lt;a href=&quot;https://nickbostrom.com/astronomical/waste.html&quot;&gt;could result in the counterfactual deaths&lt;/a&gt; of trillions of lives, squandering huge amounts of utility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-educational-inequality-treadmill&quot;&gt;The Educational Inequality Treadmill&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discussing &lt;a href=&quot;https://quillette.com/2018/05/14/the-racism-treadmill/&quot;&gt;the progressive conversation about racism&lt;/a&gt; in the United States, Coleman Hughes writes: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;wp-block-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    The disparity fallacy and the denial of cultural factors conspire to create a dynamic that I call the Racism Treadmill: as long as cultural differences continue to cause disparities between racial groups, and as long as progressives imagine that systemic racism lies behind every disparity, then no amount of progress in reducing systemic racism, however large or concrete, will ever &lt;em&gt;look&lt;/em&gt; like progress to progressives.
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can apply this same principle to disparities in educational outcomes among the rich and poor, which we might call the Educational Inequality Treadmill. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;wp-block-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    As long as [genetic differences] continue to cause disparities [in educational attainment] between [the rich and poor], and as long as [egalitarians] imagine that [lack of equality of educational opportunity] lies behind every disparity, then no amount of progress in [improving equality of educational opportunity], however large or concrete, will ever &lt;em&gt;look &lt;/em&gt;like progress to [egalitarians].
  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am certainly &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; claiming that the sort of equality of educational opportunity I’ve argued for currently exists—there’s clearly room for improvement—or that all disparities in educational attainment are due to genetics. However, I am urging those who sympathize with the egalitarian or Rawlsian take on education to consider the point at which they will cease their efforts towards equality. &lt;strong&gt;What does the end game look like given what we know from behavioral genetics about the natural distribution and mutability of intelligence and other education-related abilities?&lt;/strong&gt; At what cost are they willing to pursue their goals of equality?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though Harden and I largely agree on the empirical research, we disagree on what to do in light of it. But if there’s anything we can agree on, it’s that genes do not determine one’s moral worth, though they do &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nydailynews.com/opinion/ny-oped-an-inconvenient-truth-about-genetics-and-success-20190419-2kqam73ptzfhdes63mmx2huuuq-story.html&quot;&gt;constitute a form of privilege&lt;/a&gt;, a privilege that should engender compassion for those who didn’t receive the same &lt;a href=&quot;https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/justice-bad-luck/supplement1.html&quot;&gt;genetic luck&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll leave open the question of whether the genetically lucky have a responsibility to give back to those less fortunate—either via redistributive taxation or some other means—because as I’ve stated, we should quibble less about short term inequalities and focus more on the long-term future of our species. This isn’t meant to diminish those among us being left behind in this rapidly changing world. It’s merely to say that improving the quality of life for all human beings will, in the long run, do more to improve their plight than will palliative noble lies or finger-pointing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thanks to Jonathan Anomaly for feedback on this essay.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">“The natural distribution is neither just nor unjust; nor is it unjust that persons are born into society at some particular position. These are simply natural facts. What is just and unjust is the way that institutions deal with these facts.” John Rawls, A Theory of Justice (1971)</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How Much Does Intelligence Matter for Creative Achievement and Professional Success?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/smpy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Much Does Intelligence Matter for Creative Achievement and Professional Success?" /><published>2018-11-26T12:40:15-05:00</published><updated>2018-11-26T12:40:15-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/smpy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/smpy/">&lt;p&gt;Longitudinal studies of the highly intelligent demonstrate the importance of IQ for creative and professional achievement. The Study of Mathematically Precocious Youth (SMPY), started in the early 1970’s by Julian Stanley and now run by David Lubinski and Camila Benbow at Vanderbilt University, has tracked multiple cohorts of high-IQ individuals, the oldest of which they’ve tracked for nearly 50 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SMPY identifies gifted youths by administering the SAT, a highly g-loaded test typically taken by high school seniors, to thirteen-year-olds. In the earliest SMPY cohorts, the threshold for being accepted was the top percentile of cognitive ability in one’s age group. In some of the later cohorts, the threshold was raised to top 0.5% and even top 0.01% of cognitive ability (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gwern.net/docs/iq/smpy/2006-lubinski.pdf&quot;&gt;Lubinski and Benbow, 2006&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some have argued that cognitive ability is a threshold for success; past a certain point, it doesn’t matter (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3682183/&quot;&gt;Jauk et al., 2013&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/Outliers-Story-Success-Malcolm-Gladwell/dp/0316017930&quot;&gt;Gladwell, &lt;em&gt;Outliers&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;). This is called the “threshold hypothesis” of IQ. For example, analysis of the Terman study, a program for high-IQ individuals that predates SMPY by nearly 40 years, finds that “Termanites” (the students selected for the program), while successful, weren’t as remarkably accomplished as one might expect given their high IQs. However, this interpretation ignores the fact that the base rate of extreme accomplishment—for example, winning the Nobel prize—is extremely low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SMPY data demonstrate that the “threshold hypothesis” is likely false; IQ predicts variation in accomplishment among the general population as well as among the extremely bright. For example, 2% of the general population has a Ph.D.; among individuals in the top percentile of cognitive ability, the rate increases to 23% (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gwern.net/docs/iq/smpy/2013-kell.pdf&quot;&gt;Kell et al., 2013a, p. 5&lt;/a&gt;). Those in the bottom quartile of SAT math scores among the first three SMPY cohorts—which puts them in the top percentile of math ability among the general population—earn doctorates at a rate of 15%. However, those in the highest quartile of the SMPY cohorts (that is, those in the top 0.01% of math ability), earn doctorates at 2.7x the rate of the bottom quartile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This pattern of compounding gains of intelligence holds for many realms of creative and professional accomplishment. The odds ratio (OR) for the top quartile of SMPY (top 0.01% of math ability) compared to the bottom quartile (top 1% of math ability) are as follows (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gwern.net/docs/iq/smpy/2010-robertson.pdf&quot;&gt;Robertson et al., 2010&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Any Peer-reviewed publication (OR = 4.5)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;STEM publications (OR = 5.9)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;STEM Doctorates (OR = 18.2)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Having more than one patent (OR = 6.1)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Income in the 95th percentile (OR = 3.3)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;STEM tenure at a top 50 university (OR = 7.7)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/smpy_robertson_threshold.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%; display: block; margin: 0 auto;&quot; /&gt; 
    &lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
     &lt;b&gt; Professional Outcomes Odds Ratios by SAT-M Quartile. &lt;/b&gt; The Odds Ratio is calculated as the ratio between the proportion of outcome X (e.g. having a patent) among those in the top quartile of SMPY SAT math scores vs. the proportion in the bottom quartile.
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To state it plainly: in the U.S., those in the top 0.01% of mathematical ability are, on average, 18 times as likely to earn a STEM Ph.D. as someone in the top 1% of mathematical ability. Evidently, even among the highly intelligent, intelligence keeps on giving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intelligence differences cause variation in creative achievement among the highly accomplished, too. Among the 534 individuals with doctorates in the first three cohorts of the SMPY sample, those in the top quartile of mathematical ability are 3.07 times more likely to have at least one STEM publication and 4.89 times more likely to have a patent than those in the bottom quartile (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gwern.net/docs/iq/smpy/2008-park.pdf&quot;&gt;Park, 2008&lt;/a&gt;). Thus, even among those with doctorates, innate differences in intelligence affect the probability of getting a patent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t to say that mathematical ability is all that matters, or even that intelligence is all that matters. There are certain traits, like spatial ability, which aren’t tested on the SAT, yet add significant incremental validity in predicting who gets patents, peer-reviewed publications, and so on (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gwern.net/docs/iq/smpy/2017-wai.pdf&quot;&gt;Wai &amp;amp; Kell, 2017&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gwern.net/docs/iq/smpy/2013-kell-2.pdf&quot;&gt;Kell et al., 2013b&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lest you think the Study of Mathematically Precocious Youth is a fluke, it has been longitudinally tracking individuals for upwards of fifty years, has sample sizes in the thousands, and has been replicated in its sister program, the Duke Talent Identification Program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main takeaway is intelligence matters. It is one of a few important determinants of creative achievement and success. Though it certainly isn’t sufficient for creative and professional success, in most cases it is necessary and, among the far-right tail, produces super-linear returns.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Longitudinal studies of the highly intelligent demonstrate the importance of IQ for creative and professional achievement. The Study of Mathematically Precocious Youth (SMPY), started in the early 1970’s by Julian Stanley and now run by David Lubinski and Camila Benbow at Vanderbilt University, has tracked multiple cohorts of high-IQ individuals, the oldest of which they’ve tracked for nearly 50 years.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Science of Meditation: Behavioral Outcomes, Neural Substrates, and Inflammation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/mindfulness/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Science of Meditation: Behavioral Outcomes, Neural Substrates, and Inflammation" /><published>2018-02-17T12:28:09-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-17T12:28:09-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/science-of-mindfulness</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/mindfulness/">&lt;p&gt;Here’s my slideshow for a presentation I gave on the science of mindfulness meditation in 2018. Below I’ve attached the audio from the presentation, but beware, the quality is poor and in the second half the audio gets quieter (so you’ll have to turn up the volume).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, if you play the audio while you go through the slideshow, it will help explain a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;100%&quot; height=&quot;166&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; frameborder=&quot;no&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay&quot; src=&quot;https://w.soundcloud.com/player/?url=https%3A//api.soundcloud.com/tracks/401996169&amp;amp;color=%233d3226&amp;amp;auto_play=false&amp;amp;hide_related=false&amp;amp;show_comments=true&amp;amp;show_user=true&amp;amp;show_reposts=false&amp;amp;show_teaser=true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;font-size: 10px; color: #cccccc;line-break: anywhere;word-break: normal;overflow: hidden;white-space: nowrap;text-overflow: ellipsis; font-family: Interstate,Lucida Grande,Lucida Sans Unicode,Lucida Sans,Garuda,Verdana,Tahoma,sans-serif;font-weight: 100;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/adamlgreen&quot; title=&quot;adamlgreen&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; style=&quot;color: #cccccc; text-decoration: none;&quot;&gt;adamlgreen&lt;/a&gt; · &lt;a href=&quot;https://soundcloud.com/adamlgreen/meditation-presentation-audio&quot; title=&quot;Meditation Presentation Audio&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; style=&quot;color: #cccccc; text-decoration: none;&quot;&gt;Meditation Presentation Audio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/e/2PACX-1vQXcnqRQiqmhzXRbjmcPysOC1pIN5m9De9LAb-IknrF5qzq2qDqr5zGu9ql5fbXYw/embed?start=false&amp;amp;loop=false&amp;amp;delayms=60000&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; width=&quot;750&quot; height=&quot;450&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot; mozallowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot; webkitallowfullscreen=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update 08/2019: It seems that mindfulness research has fallen prey to the replication crisis. There appears to be substantial publication bias. See &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/news/power-of-positive-thinking-skews-mindfulness-studies-1.19776&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://qz.com/668887/a-new-study-suggests-mindfulness-isnt-quite-as-miraculous-as-weve-been-led-to-believe/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, for example. So, take everything said above with a slightly larger grain of salt. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Here’s my slideshow for a presentation I gave on the science of mindfulness meditation in 2018. Below I’ve attached the audio from the presentation, but beware, the quality is poor and in the second half the audio gets quieter (so you’ll have to turn up the volume).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Searching for the Self: Predictive Processing and the Evolution of Subjectivity</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/searching-for-self/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Searching for the Self: Predictive Processing and the Evolution of Subjectivity" /><published>2018-02-03T12:01:52-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-03T12:01:52-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/searching-for-self</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/searching-for-self/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The precursor to this essay, written around a year earlier, can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://adamlgreen.com/conscious-pt-1/&quot;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Physicalism satisfyingly explains much of how reality works. We readily accept the explanation that heat is the motion of molecules and that DNA is the code of life. However, when talking about the experience of seeing the color red or the taste of coffee, it seems a purely physical explanation of color perception or gustation is lacking. What it lacks, according to many, is the phenomenal, what-it-is-likeness of the experience, something that can only be known from a first-person perspective (Nagel, 1974). No matter how well we explain sensation and perception in physical terms, no explanation will ever be epistemically satisfying; we will always face an “explanatory gap” between our qualitative experience and our explanations of it in physical terms (Levine, 1983).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The explanatory gap is predicated on the existence of a metaphysically-special class of properties that are distinct from the physical: the so-called mental or phenomenal properties. However, as I’ll argue, these properties do not exist, and our belief that they do is due to an erroneous belief in the existence of a metaphysically-special subject of experience to whom we attribute these mental properties—the self. Once we show that there is no subject of experience, we’ll see that the apparent existence of the explanatory gap is due to the limits of human intuition, not the existence of a unique class of mental properties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aim of this paper is to provide a deflationary account of selfhood. I aim to explain where our intuitions about selfhood come from, why they are a poor guide to Truth, and how they can be shifted. In doing so, I hope to shift your intuitions about the existence of a subject of experience, and by extension, the existence of mental properties. I will argue that what we call “the self”—the subject that witnesses all the events of consciousness—is a “hallucination” generated by the brain, and this hallucination can, in principle and (eventually) in practice, be explained in fully physical terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My argument is divided into three parts. In Part 1, I’ll explain why we ought to treat physicalism as the null hypothesis and favor it prima facie; I’ll then define the term “self,” and explain where our intuitions about subjectivity come from. In Part 2, I’ll discuss the predictive processing theory, which claims that our brain predicts and generates what we call reality in order to reduce uncertainty; I’ll then situate the &lt;em&gt;the self&lt;/em&gt; within this framework and explain why would have been selected for by evolution. In Part 3, I’ll explain how even if we provide a comprehensive explanation of the self, we will never intuitively grasp the fact that what we call consciousness is a purely physical process; therefore, for all intents and purposes, the metaphysical fact of the matter isn’t important, because it will always intuitively “feel” like we are undergoing a subjective experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;11-the-physicalist-null-hypothesis&quot;&gt;1.1 The physicalist null hypothesis&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the purposes of this paper, I’ll take a Bayesian perspective and argue that a physicalist (i.e., naturalistic, as opposed to some variety of dualism or panpsychism) explanation of the self—the apparent existence of a metaphysically-special self is a hallucination generated through purely physical processes—is more likely true than a dualist explanation—there exist non-physical properties which supervene on the physical. I think a physical explanation is more likely because of induction: those things which we thought were beyond physical explanation—how life is different from non-life—were ultimately explained in physical terms—respiration, excretion, etc. So it seems safe to assume that the march of reductionism will eventually explain everything in terms of basic physics. We can call this our physicalist null hypothesis. The alternative hypothesis is that we will never be able to explain certain phenomena—specifically the what-it-is-likeness of qualitative experience—in physical terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;12-intuitions-about-the-self&quot;&gt;1.2 Intuitions about the self&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The self&lt;/em&gt; is a nebulous, multidimensional term. As I’ll show, this is because what we call the self is a pastiche of disparate mental states. But for the purposes of argument, we can distinguish between two types of selfhood, broadly speaking. The &lt;em&gt;narrative self&lt;/em&gt; is the volitional agent with which you identify across time. This self has goals and is referred to as “I”. It is implicated in social thinking. The &lt;em&gt;embodied self&lt;/em&gt; is your representation of your body in space: the boundaries between you and the external world and your interoceptive, visceral sensations like hunger, pain, or drowsiness. It appears to be the immediate subject of what some call &lt;em&gt;qualia&lt;/em&gt; (Nagel, 1974).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You refer to both these aspects of the self all the time. If someone asks you who is experiencing the sensations and percepts your brain generates, you say “I am,” not “the amalgamation of atoms that form the human being that is uttering this sentence is.”  When you speak, you refer to “me” and “my,” as if there were some transtemporal entity like a soul sitting inside your skull. &lt;strong&gt;Thus, even if we aren’t substance dualists, we all act as if we were.&lt;/strong&gt; We readily distinguish between “I” and the outside world. &lt;strong&gt;It is in this way that the existence of the self is intuitive.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if you simply direct attention inward, toward the contents of experience in the present moment—the feeling of the seat pressing up into the body, the temperature of the air in the room—you will find that there are only sensations.&lt;a href=&quot;#_ftn3&quot; name=&quot;_ftnref3&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[3]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; The feeling of self arises when you connect these sensations to another sensation: that of being a subject of experience. A modified version of the Block’s (2007) refrigerator light illusion applies here: when we aren’t introspecting on the nature of selfhood—e.g. when we’re lost in a good conversation or deep in a meditative state—it’s uncertain if the light of selfhood is on or off. But when we check to see if it’s there—when we wonder what the other person thinks of us, or think about some social fumble we made in the past, or actively think about the nature of selfhood—the light of selfhood is on (Blackmore, 2016).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;13-an-evolutionary-account-of-intuitions&quot;&gt;1.3 An evolutionary account of intuitions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I claimed that the existence of the self is intuitive. By this I mean that the feeling of being a subject of experience produces a minimal amount of internal confusion. It simply &lt;em&gt;feels&lt;/em&gt; like it’s true. However, as the history of science shows, just because something feels intuitive doesn’t mean it’s true; and just because something feels unintuitive doesn’t mean it’s necessarily false. The idea that the Earth orbits the Sun is unintuitive; the idea that our biological blueprint is encoded in a substrate called DNA is unintuitive; and the idea that our universe is composed of microscopic particles is unintuitive. Yet we treat these explanations as true because their explanatory power is satisfying enough to make us disregard our intuitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Selfhood is intuitive because evolution selected for us to be prosocial, naive-realists that survive and reproduce. It selected for us experience life as if we are looking through a transparent, diaphanous pane of glass onto the contents of experience (Moore, 1903; Tye 2002). It did not select for us to see the pane of glass and try to explain what it is made of. This is one of the reasons why arguing the self is a hallucination is so unintuitive: our given “epistemic situation with regards to consciousness”—feeling that we are subjects with direct, epistemically-privileged access to the contents of our subjective experience—makes it difficult to rationally question the nature of consciousness (Ball, 2009).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But again, just because feeling we are subjects of experience is intuitive does not make it true. Assuming intuitions are a good guide to truth is a naturalistic fallacy of sorts. It’s fallacious because it presupposes that evolution selected for us to understand the true nature of reality, which, as just established, is not how evolution necessarily works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visual illusions illustrate this well: we are constantly generating reality through an internal model, a model that uses heuristics and is biased is profound ways. We overcome these biases by extending our cognition with empirical tools: the telescope, the microscope, and mathematics, for example. In the case of the Ebbinghaus illusion (see the following page), while the left orange circle appears smaller than the right, we can measure the diameters of the two circles to see that they are actually the same size. This empirical explanation is satisfying enough for us to disregard the intuition that one circle is smaller than the other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/ebbinghaus.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%; display: block; margin: 0 auto;&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
        The Ebbinghaus illusion.
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;21-the-predictive-processing-theory-illusions-and-hallucinations&quot;&gt;2.1 The predictive processing theory, illusions and hallucinations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setting aside the self for a moment, let’s turn our attention to the predictive processing theory of cognition, an overarching model of how the brain works. The model argues that our brain does not directly see reality in a naive-realist fashion; rather, our brain is constantly predicting and simulating what we call reality. We can explain the Ebbinghaus illusion through this model. Per the model, our misinterpretation of the visual data is caused by our prior expectations (i.e. our priors). Our brain uses a top-down generative model—items surrounded by smaller items look bigger—to construct your visual reality from the incoming bottom-up sense data. Illusions like the Ebbinghaus illusion occur when our these models are tricked (Clark, 2016). However, these models are quite useful, as they allow us to simplify all the sensory data the brain receives; were we not to have them, our brains would be overflowing with information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On its own, the predictive processing theory is nothing new. In fact, it originates in the work of 19th century physician Hermann von Helmholtz (Clark, 2016). However, the so-called Bayesian brain hypothesis adds a probabilistic, quantitative component to the predictive processing model and allows us to cash out our psychological models in terms of Bayesian language (Friston, 2010). Recent work (Abbott et al., 1997; Yu &amp;amp; Dayan, 2005; Doya, 2002; Friston, 2010) in computational neuroscience supports the idea that we are Bayesian prediction machines, showing that belief and uncertainty are instantiated on a neural level through changes in synaptic gain (i.e. changes in the strength of connection between the presynaptic and postsynaptic terminal) and competition between local populations of neurons, among other mechanisms. As Anil Seth and Karl Friston put it, “the brain is not an elaborate stimulus-response link but a statistical organ that actively generates explanations for the stimuli it encounters” (Seth &amp;amp; Friston, 2016).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Bayesian brain hypothesis is intimately tied to the free-energy principle, an idea from statistical thermodynamics and information theory. It states that “any self-organizing system that is at equilibrium with its environment must minimize its free energy” (Friston, 2010). For our purposes, free energy is synonymous with entropy, a measure of disorder or uncertainty. Physical systems (like humans) must reduce uncertainty in order to resist their tendency toward entropy. We do this by changing our predictions about the environment—predictive processing—and by changing the data we receive by changing our environment—so-called “active inference” (Friston, 2010). I will expand on the importance of the free-energy principle in section 2.4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;22-predictive-processing-of-the-self-model&quot;&gt;2.2 Predictive processing of the self model&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the predictive processing theory and Bayesian brain hypothesis in place, we can now step outside our limited epistemic situation and put subjective experience within a broader context. If we take the predictive processing theory seriously, it has some two interesting implications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do not directly “see,” “hear,” or “smell” anything. All our sensations and perceptions are internally generated, going through some sort of filtering based on top-down control. For example, when you hear a car alarm go off, your brain slowly habituates, attenuating the signal. We can explain this in Bayesian terms: the sound initially had a high degree of surprise—you weren’t expecting a car alarm to go off—hence why it was so salient to you. But over time you came to expect the repeated blaring of the car horn and it became less salient. The car horn stayed the same, but repeated sense data caused your top-down predictive models to expect the sound, allowing you to suppress your Bayesian surprise; this manifests itself in the experience of not hearing the car as loudly (unless you attend to the sound again). Or, instead of habituating to the sound, perhaps you went somewhere where the horn couldn’t be heard, a form of active inference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As shown with the Ebbinghaus illusion, our internal models often cause us to misinterpret incoming sense data. However, if we are constantly predicting and constructing reality in a top-down fashion instead of passively viewing it from the bottom-up, then we might not just be subject to the occasional illusion: we may be hallucinating our reality all the time. By hallucinate, I do not mean that we are misperceiving incoming sense data. I mean that we erroneously generate sensations from within, e.g. the sensation that all the physical things happening in the present moment are part of some grand subjective experience we are undergoing. This hallucination is at the core of what it feels like to be a self, to be a locus of consciousness. It is bold to claim the self is a hallucination, but in the next section I’ll explain the ways this hallucination may be implemented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;23-the-rubber-hand-illusion-and-other-experimental-perturbations-of-interoception&quot;&gt;2.3 The rubber-hand illusion and other experimental perturbations of interoception&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rubber hand illusion (RHI) is a simple example of how the embodied self is integrated and how it can easily be perturbed. In the RHI, the subject’s hand rests on the table and is occluded from view by box; a rubber hand is then placed in front of the subject. As the subject looks at the rubber hand, the experimenter strokes both hands simultaneously. Subjects report feeling like the rubber hand is their own  (Botvinick &amp;amp; Cohen, 1998). When the rubber hand is threatened—for example, when the experimenter stabs it with a fork—many subjects elicit a statistically significant response in areas of the brain associated with anxiety such as the insula (Ehrsson, 2007).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The RHI is quite a simple example of how the predictive mechanisms of the brain can be fooled. But recent experimental work (Suzuki et al., 2013) shows that our sense of embodied selfhood can be perturbed in much more significant ways. In one experiment, subjects wore a virtual reality (VR) headset and a heartrate monitor. The subjects looked at their hand through the VR headset. In one condition the hand pulsed in sync with their heartbeat; in another condition it did not. Subjects reported feeling much more identified with the VR hand when it pulsed in sync with their heartbeat, suggesting  that the embodied selfhood model of the brain inferred the hand to be part of the body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These experiments and others (see Slater et al. 2010 for an example of a VR-induced full-body illusion) suggest that feelings of body ownership are due to multiple levels of feedback mechanisms between interoceptive signals your brain receives (e.g. your brain unconsciously monitoring your heart rate) and the brain’s predictions of these signals. For example, your hand feels like &lt;em&gt;your hand&lt;/em&gt; because the visual data you receive when you watch it move is similar to the internal data that generate the movement of the hand. When the visual data does not match up with the motor data, this creates a large “prediction error” and tells your brain to update its predictions. This self-modelling of the body through prediction coding has been called “active interoception” (Seth &amp;amp; Friston, 2016). Per this model, what we call emotions are high-level predictive concepts that help our brain make sense of the low-level autonomic signals it receives from throughout the body. When we stub our toe, what we identify as pain is caused by high-level prediction of the causes of the inflammation in our toe, the localization of those signals to our toe, and a slight decrease in affect, among other things (Seth, 2013).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both the RHI and the VR experiment show how the embodied self is a generative model our brain uses to make sense of the environment. Thus the hand that is your own is not necessarily the one that is attached to your body, but the one you &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; is attached to your body. But, as I’ve argued, there is no special subject of experience to whom the hand belongs; the feeling of being a subject is merely a hallucination the brain generates in order to reduce uncertainty, as I’ll show in the next section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;24-an-evolutionary-explanation-of-embodied-selfhood&quot;&gt;2.4 An evolutionary explanation of embodied selfhood&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Selfhood is a way of minimizing free energy, of better predicting the nature of future state spaces of the environment and thus being better adapted to them. Setting aside our human conception of selfhood, imagine a single-cell organism whose survival is dependent on maintaining boundaries with the external world. In order to maintain homeostasis, certain things need to come in (e.g. food), and other things need to stay out (e.g. intruders). The cell accomplishes this feat by recognizing patterns in the environment, patterns of what is part of itself and what is not. Though it does not think “my DNA is part of me and this virus is not,” it acts as if this were the case: it uses its proto-immune-system to attack intruders and protect its internal environment. This is a form of basic selfhood, distinguishing between that which is me (i.e. that which has similar genetic interests as I do) and that which is not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we call embodied selfhood comes from the same imperative the single-cell organism was following: maintain homeostasis by controlling the boundary between me and the outside world. Yes, our sense of selfhood is much more complicated, a pattern-recognition schema that evolution produced through billions of years of selection. But it is the same form of pattern-recognition nonetheless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we call the narrative self is the an extremely high-level version of this embodied selfhood. There are reasons why evolution would have selected for us to attribute a higher-level narrative self to ourselves and others. Attribution of a narrative self to ourselves allows us to plan our own behavior, which would have been hugely beneficial for survival and reproduction. Attribution of a narrative self to others allows us to predict their behavior and therefore cooperate with them. This facilitates the emergence of prosocial behavior, hence why it was selected (perhaps via group selection.) Add on top of that the ability to articulate beliefs and desires in terms of language, and a positive feedback loop would develop. Framed in this light, it’s clear why we feel we are subjects of experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;25-narrative-selfhood-and-inducing-ego-dissolution&quot;&gt;2.5 Narrative selfhood and inducing ego dissolution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evolution did not select for us to cut through the hallucination of the narrative self, just as it didn’t select for us to question our agency and the nature of free will. However, empirical work on altered states of consciousness induced by psychedelics and meditation show that the hallucination of the self can dissolve temporarily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Psychedelics and meditation often occasion what is termed “oceanic boundlessness” or “ego dissolution,” a breakdown of what we’ve henceforth referred to as the narrative self (Carhart-Harris &amp;amp; Nutt, 2010). One might view these altered states of consciousness as hallucinations. However, I believe that they are examples of the dissolution of high-level predictive schema the brain uses to generate the hallucination of the self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carhart-Harris et al. (2014) has recently proposed a theory to explain psychedelic states called the Entropic Brain hypothesis. Using functional connectivity neuroimaging, which measures correlations between different voxels in the brain while at rest, they argue that psychedelics experiences are an example of &lt;em&gt;primary states&lt;/em&gt;, those characterized by low information integration, and thus high entropy. Conversely, normal conscious waking life is an example of a &lt;em&gt;secondary state&lt;/em&gt; characterized by low entropy and a high degree of information integration in the brain.&lt;a href=&quot;#_ftn4&quot; name=&quot;_ftnref4&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[4]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carhart-Harris et al. measured what they call “entropy” by looking at the variance within a network of the brain (e.g. the variance in activation of voxels within the default mode network); those networks with high variance were defined as having high levels of entropy. There were two condition, the control condition and the experimental psilocybin condition. When looking at subjects in a normal conscious state, they found little entropy in all brain networks. In the experimental psilocybin condition, they found increased entropy in many of the higher-level networks, like the default mode network (which has been associated with social cognition and the narrative self) and the salience network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
&lt;img loading=&quot;lazy&quot; src=&quot;/assets/img/Homological-scaffold-of-placebo-v-psilocybin.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%; display: block; margin: 0 auto;&quot; /&gt; 
&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;
        Homological scaffolds representing brain network connectivity in the placebo (left) and psilocybin (right) groups.
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Carhart-Harris et al. did not offer a fully mechanistic account of how psychedelics such as psilocybin cut through the hallucination of the self, their entropic brain hypothesis is a promising explanation, and fits in nicely with the predictive processing account of cognition. They argue that psychedelics relax our top-down priors, the high level predictive schema we employ in day-to-day life such as “this is who I am” and “this is my body,” hence the feelings of ego dissolution and oceanic boundlessness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Psychedelic experiences and their neural correlates are not evidence for the self being a hallucination. However, they do show that it is possible to cut through the first-person, transparent perspective through which we view the world, and thus shift our intuitions about the nature of experience in profound ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;31-on-shifting-intuitions&quot;&gt;3.1 On shifting intuitions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the previous two sections I’ve attempted to define the multiple facets of the term &lt;em&gt;self,&lt;/em&gt; situate it within the predictive processing theory, and provide an account of how and why the brain generates it. However, you may still feel that you are a subject of experience. This is understandable. As I’ve stated, evolution selected for our intuitions about selfhood to be deeply hardwired in our brain; these intuitions are only changed through serious effort (e.g. a 3-month vipassana meditation retreat or a strong dose of psychedelics.) From a functionalist perspective, I myself probably don’t even believe the self is a hallucination (see, I just referred to “I,” “myself,” and “believe.”)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve argued that these intuitions ought to be doubted because we are merely machines running complex software. The real authority, and where we should look for explanations of consciousness, is the designer of it all: the forces of evolution by natural selection. However, even if you have your doubts, if for a moment we assume the null hypothesis that our experience of selfhood is nothing more physical patterns of neural firing, where are we left metaphysically?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are left with the following: there’s no Cartesian theater or spotlight of consciousness. Every neuron in your brain is an actor and every glial cell a member of the crew, and they’re orchestrating the most magnificent theatre production imaginable. It’s just something they all happen to do as an accident of billions of years of evolution. Sometimes the theatrical ensemble may act as if there is an audience there, but alas, there is no audience. There is no person sitting in the lighting room and moving the spotlight of consciousness, and there is no Cartesian theatre in the brain of the hypothetical person sitting in the lighting room. If there were, we’d face an infinite regress, the homunculus problem. We can avoid this by biting the bullet and accepting that what we call the self is an extremely strong hallucination our brain generates in order to facilitate homeostasis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With respect to qualia, if there is no metaphysically-special self, then there is no reason to think that we have epistemically-privileged access to our conscious experience; this is because there is no self, no subject of experience, that is distinct from the sensations (i.e. patterns of neural firing) being experienced. While the organism that is you has direct access to the neural firing going on in its brain, this doesn’t mean that you—the hallucinatory subject of experience—has qualitatively distinct access to what’s going on in your brain as compared to me. Thus we’d have to bite the bullet on qualia being some ineffable, metaphysically-special class of properties which we have access to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It follows that if I had an exact atom-for-atom representation of what’s going on in your brain and had a sophisticated enough model of my own neural architecture, then I’d understand your experience as well as you do. And if I had sophisticated technology that allowed me to selectively activate my brain in very precise ways, then I’d be able to recreate the “experience” you’re undergoing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might object, “if everything I perceive is a hallucination, does anything exist at all?” As a physicalist, I’d say yes.&lt;a href=&quot;#_ftn5&quot; name=&quot;_ftnref5&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[5]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; The world is made of physical matter—atoms, quarks, etc.—and our brain represents different organizations of this matter as patterns of neural firing. But that is it. Believing—that is, acting as if you believe and saying you believe—that there exists some class of metaphysically-special properties called “the mental” is merely a result of this complex neural firing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also follows that the representation of “cat” in my brain does not possess some special mental property of “catness.” When we refer to the concept “cat,” we’re referring to a physical pattern found in the weighted connections between neurons in human brains; this pattern is isomorphic to those organisms out in the world we call cats. For example, their is some level of retinotopic mapping in higher level visual areas such that my neural representation of “cat” is cat-like, in the sense it bears some, albeit convoluted, resemblance to the physical structure of cats. We say “that’s a cat” when we see what is putatively a cat; and if you ask me about my cat, Dixie, I might report experiencing a visual representation of an animal that likes to kill mice and birds and bring them to my doorstep. But we can cash this all out in functionalist terms, and so there’s no need to appeal to a special mental experience which supervenes on the physical representation of a cat in your brain. The appearance of this special mental component is merely part of the greater hallucination of selfhood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;32-realism-pragmatism-and-the-intentional-stance&quot;&gt;3.2 Realism, Pragmatism, and the intentional stance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We ought to favor a physical explanation of the self over a dualist one if only because it’s more consistent with physicalist explanations of the world, and therefore more parsimonious. In addition, physicalist theories offer greater potential explanatory power, whereas dualist theories inevitably run into a wall (or a gap, as it were.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That being said, just as we can’t live acting as if cats aren’t real, we can’t live acting as if the self isn’t real. Believing the self isn’t real would lead to a high degree of psychopathology, something akin to dissociative identity disorder. So, for the sake of social function, we ought to take “intentional stance” towards the self, acting as if it exists and that other human beings are real subjects of experience (Dennett, 1991). If we didn’t treat other people as agential, subjective beings, society would collapse. So in the Pragmatist, Darwinian sense of Truth, selves do indeed exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;References:&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abbott, L. F., Varela, J. A., Sen, K. &amp;amp; Nelson, S. B. 1997. “Synaptic Depression and Cortical Gain Control.” &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt; 275:220–224.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ball, Derek. 2009. “There Are No Phenomenal Concepts.” &lt;em&gt;Mind,&lt;/em&gt; 118(472): 935-962.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blackmore, Susan. 2016. “Delusions of Consciousness.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Consciousness Studies&lt;/em&gt;, 23(11): 52–64.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blanke, Olaf &amp;amp; Thomas Metzinger. 2008. “Full-body Illusions and Minimal Phenomenal Selfhood.” &lt;em&gt;Trends in Cognitive Science&lt;/em&gt;, 13(1): 7-13.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Block, Ned. 2007. “Consciousness, Accessibility, and the Mesh Between Psychology and Neuroscience.” &lt;em&gt;Behavioral and Brain Sciences&lt;/em&gt;. 30: 481-548.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Botvinick, Matthew, &amp;amp; Jonathan Cohen. 1998. “Rubber Hands ‘Feel’ Touch That Eyes See.” &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; 391(19): 756.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carhart-Harris, R. L., and Nutt, D. J. 2010. “User Perceptions of the Benefits and Harms of Hallucinogenic Drug Use: a Web-based Questionnaire Study.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Substance Use,&lt;/em&gt; 15: 283–300.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carhart-Harris, R.L., Leech, Robert, Hellyer, P.J., Shanahan, Murray, Feilding, Amanda, Tagliazucchi, Enzo, Chialvo, D.R., &amp;amp; David Nutt. 2014. “The Entropic Brain: A Theory of Conscious States Informed by Neuroimaging with Psychedelic Drugs.” &lt;em&gt;Frontiers in Human Neuroscience&lt;/em&gt;, 8(20): 1-22.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clark, Andy. 2015. &lt;em&gt;Surfing Uncertainty: Prediction, Action, and the Embodied Mind&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford University Press.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dennett, Daniel C. 1991. “Real Patterns.” &lt;em&gt;The Journal of Philosophy&lt;/em&gt;, 88(1): 27-51.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doya, K. 2002. “Metalearning and neuromodulation.” &lt;em&gt;Neural Networks.&lt;/em&gt; 15: 495–506.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ehrsson, Henrik H, Wiech, Katja, Weiskopf, Nikolaus, Dolan, Raymond J., &amp;amp; Richard E. Passingham. 2007. “Threatening a Rubber Hand that You Feel is Yours Elicits Cortical Anxiety Response.” &lt;em&gt;PNAS&lt;/em&gt;, 104(23): 9828-9833.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friston, Karl. 2010. “The Free-energy Principle: A Unified Brain Theory?” &lt;em&gt;Nature Reviews Neuroscience&lt;/em&gt;, 11:127-138.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Levine, Joseph. 1983. “Materialism and Qualia: The Explanatory Gap.” &lt;em&gt;Pacific Philosophical Quarterly&lt;/em&gt;, 64: 354–361.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Limanowski, J. &amp;amp; Blankenburg F. 2013. “Minimal Self-Models and the Free Energy Principle.” &lt;em&gt;Frontiers of Human Neuroscience&lt;/em&gt; 7:547.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moore, G.E. 1903. “The Refutation of Idealism.” &lt;em&gt;Mind&lt;/em&gt;, 12: 433-53.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nagel, Thomas. 1974. “What Is It Like to Be a Bat?” &lt;em&gt;The Philosophical Review&lt;/em&gt;, 83(4): 435–450.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Raatikainen, Panu. 2015. “Gödel’s Incompleteness Theorems.” &lt;em&gt;The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy,&lt;/em&gt; ed. Edward N. Zalta. &lt;a href=&quot;https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/spr2015/entries/goedel-incompleteness/&quot;&gt;https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/spr2015/entries/goedel-incompleteness/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seth, Anil K. 2013. “Interoceptive Inference, Emotion, and the Embodied Self.” &lt;em&gt;Trends in Cognitive Science&lt;/em&gt;, 17(11): 565-573.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seth, Anil K., &amp;amp; Karl Friston. 2016. “Active Interoception and the Emotional Brain.” &lt;em&gt;Phil Trans. R. Soc. B&lt;/em&gt; 371: 1-10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slater M., Spanlang B., Sanchez-Vives M.V., &amp;amp; Blanke O. 2010. “First Person Experience of Body Transfer in Virtual Reality.” PLoS ONE 5(5): e10564.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suzuki, Keisuke, Garfinkel, S.N., Critchley, H.D., &amp;amp; Anil K. Seth. 2013. “Multisensory Integration across Exteroceptive and Interoceptive Domains Modulates Self-experience in the Rubber Hand Illusion.” &lt;em&gt;Neuropsychologia,&lt;/em&gt; 51(13): 2909-2917.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tononi, G. 2012. “Integrated Information Theory of Consciousness: An Updated Account.” &lt;em&gt;Archives Italiennes de Biologie,&lt;/em&gt; 150: 290-326.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tye, Michael. 2002. “Representationalism and the Transparency of Experience.” &lt;em&gt;Noûs,&lt;/em&gt; 36(1): 137-151.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yu, A. J. &amp;amp; Dayan, P. 2005. “Uncertainty, Neuromodulation and Attention.” &lt;em&gt;Neuron&lt;/em&gt; 46: 681–692.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ftnref1&quot; name=&quot;&amp;quot;_ftn1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Granted, it still currently leaves many questions unanswered, such as what preceded the Big Bang, but these questions seem to be answerable in principle.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;#_ftnref2&quot; name=&quot;_ftn2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; This is analogous to mathematician Kurt Gödel’s 2nd Incompleteness Theorem: no formal system of logic can prove its own consistency (Raatikainen, “Gödel’s Incompleteness Theorems”). It’s also analogous to David Hume’s claim about not being able to derive a normative “ought” from only a descriptive “is.” Only once you’ve established your axiomatic “ought”—e.g. the highest moral imperative is reducing the suffering of conscious beings—can descriptive facts about the world be brought to bear on ethics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#_ftnref3&quot; name=&quot;_ftn3&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[3]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Or, speaking from a physicalist perspective, there are only patterns of neural firing that you post-hoc identify as sensations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#_ftnref4&quot; name=&quot;_ftn4&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[4]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; This measure of entropy is inversely related to what Tononi (2012) calls phi, integrated information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#_ftnref5&quot; name=&quot;_ftn5&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[5]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; But, as stated in section 1.1, I have no proof of this. It’s merely a claim I take to be axiomatic.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The precursor to this essay, written around a year earlier, can be found here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Using Neuroimaging to Predict Recidivism and Identify Psychopaths</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/psychopathy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Using Neuroimaging to Predict Recidivism and Identify Psychopaths" /><published>2017-12-27T03:48:15-05:00</published><updated>2017-12-27T03:48:15-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/psychopathy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/psychopathy/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The intersection of cognitive neuroscience and the law—called &lt;em&gt;neurolaw&lt;/em&gt;—is a rapidly growing field of research. Many are excited by the potential of neuroscience to improve everything from criminal sentencing to rehabilitation of criminals (Jones et al., 2013). In this paper I will focus on the application of neuroimaging to psychopathy, and specifically on how it can be used to predict future recidivism—aptly named &lt;em&gt;neuroprediction&lt;/em&gt;—and identify psychopaths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Psychopaths make up less than 1% of the U.S. population, yet commit 30% of all violent crime, costing us $250-400 billion dollars per year (Kiehl, 2010). Thus, if neuroimaging can improve our ability to diagnose psychopathy and predict recidivism, it will be quite the boon to society. However, as with other promising technologies, there are many methodological and ethical issues that arise from our growing neuropredictive powers. My thesis is that if we exercise sufficient caution and thoroughly vet these neuroprediction tools, then we ought to use them in our criminal justice system, for they are only going to give us better, more accurate information and improve upon our current forms of risk assessment. The real ethical issue is how we use this predictive information, but this issue isn’t unique to neuroimaging: it’s an issue all forms of predictive evidence face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Psychopathy Explained&lt;/em&gt;, I will define psychopathy, explain how we measure it, and explain clinical and actuarial violence risk assessment. In &lt;em&gt;Neuroprediction Examples&lt;/em&gt;, I will provide two examples in which neuroimaging is applied to psychopathy and one where it is applied to predicting recidivism is general. In &lt;em&gt;Methodological and Scientific Concerns&lt;/em&gt;, I will discuss issues general to all three examples and to the practice of treating people differently on the basis of brain scans. Finally, in &lt;em&gt;Applications and Ethical Concerns&lt;/em&gt;, I will discuss potential applications of neuroprediction and address the unique ethical issues they might give rise to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;psychopathy-explained&quot;&gt;Psychopathy Explained&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Psychopathy is a psychiatric disorder composed of multiple traits. The Hare Psychopathy Checklist-Revised (PCL-R), a twenty item diagnostic exam, is currently the standard for measuring these traits and identifying psychopaths (Kiehl, 2010). Items in the PCL-R measure two factors of psychopathy. Factor 1 items measure traits related to “emotional and interpersonal relationships, such as superficial charm, egocentricity, grandiosity, deceitfulness and manipulativeness, and absence of remorse, guilt, or empathy”; Factor 2 items measure traits such as “impulsivity, poor behavioral controls, proneness to boredom, poor life planning, and irresponsibility” (Kiehl, 2010, 48). Thus, psychopathy is a complex disorder with distinct factors that can be measured via the PCL-R. However, because it is based on self-report, the PCL-R is not a perfect metric. For example, one of the Factor 1 items of the PCL-R measures pathological lying; one can imagine how difficult it would be to measure this trait via self-report (Hulbert, 2015).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PCL-R is one part of a much broader violence risk assessment that is important to the legal process. Risk assessment factors into everything from sentencing to rehabilitation of criminals. An important distinction to note is that of “clinical assessment” vs. “actuarial assessment” of violence risk (Nadelhoffer, 2012a). Clinical assessment is based on a mental health professional’s interaction with a patient and what they believe the patient’s future behavior will be like. However, this type of assessment is prone to the biases of the mental health practitioner, and some claim that psychologists and psychiatrists’ predictions are no better than “flipping coins in the courtroom” (Nadelhoffer, 2012a; Ennis &amp;amp; Litwack, 1974). Conversely, actuarial assessment is a probabilistic approach to violence risk, which takes into account a host of factors such as age, gender, impulsivity, family and work history, history of violence, social networks and mental disorders (Nadelhoffer, 2012a, 77). The PCL-R often factors into these actuarial violence risk assessments. However, the PCL-R is not as robust as desired, so perhaps neuroimaging can improve our risk assessment models (81).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-neuroprediction-examples&quot;&gt;3 Neuroprediction Examples&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;structural-mri&quot;&gt;Structural MRI&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steele et al. trained machine learning algorithms to differentiate between psychopathic and non-psychopathic adolescents using structural MRI and other measures such as IQ and age. Psychopaths tend to exhibit “structural and cognitive deficits originating in paralimbic areas,” and therefore Steele et al. chose thirteen of these areas as their a priori regions of interest and measured grey matter volume in density in these ROIs (2). Their subject pool was composed of 71 “incarcerated youth with elevated psychopathic traits,” 72 “incarcerated youth with low-psychopathic traits,” and 21 “non-incarcerated youth as healthy controls” (1). These categorizations were based on the results of the PCL: YV, a youth version of the PCL-R (2).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their machine learning algorithm based on grey matter density was able to differentiate between high-psychopathic individuals and healthy controls with an overall accuracy of 82.61%. However, their classifier which used only age and IQ was actually able to better differentiate between these individuals, with an overall accuracy of 83.10% (5). When the classifiers were used to differentiate between low-psychopathic individuals and healthy controls, a similar trend emerged, with the age and IQ-based classifier doing slightly better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;resting-state-functional-connectivity-rsfmri&quot;&gt;Resting-state functional connectivity (rsfMRI)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Philippi et al. examined the resting state functional connectivity (rsfMRI) of 142 prison inmates, 46 of whom were psychopathic. They wanted to see how the functional connectivity of the default mode, frontoparietal, and cingulo-opercular networks (abbreviated DMN, FPN, and CON, respectively) related to PCL-R scores, and more specifically, scores on each factor of the PCL-R (6070). In their within-group analysis of psychopaths, they found that “higher PCL-R scores were associated significantly diminished connectivity between the right (R) IPS [intraparietal sulcus] and the bilateral dACC of the CON and the right precuneus of the FPN” (6071). Their between-group analysis resulted in similar findings, with only seed regions in the FPN showing significant differences in functional connectivity between the two groups. They conclude that “diminished parietal–dACC connectivity is a robust neurobiological correlate of psychopathy” (6075).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, Philippi et al. actually found a dissociation in functional connectivity of the different factors of psychopathy. For example, “higher Factor 1 scores”—which measures interpersonal/affective traits— “were associated with significantly decreased connectivity between the medial and lateral regions of the DMN,” whereas “higher Factor 2 scores were associated with significantly increased functional connectivity between the medial prefrontal and parietal regions of the DMN” (6071). This apparent dissociation between the two factors of psychopathy is unintuitive and suggests that psychiatric disorders such as psychopathy aren’t as simple as we might make them out to be. Therefore, we ought to consider specific biomarkers for Factor 1 and Factor 2 of psychopathy when doing our risk assessment and designing our rehabilitation programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;task-based-fmri&quot;&gt;Task-based fMRI&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aharoni et al. did a longitudinal study looking at how anterior cingulate cortex (ACC) activity during the performance of an impulse control task correlated with recidivism. Their subject pool was composed of 96 adult offenders—those who had committed crimes in the past; however, only some, not all, of the participants were psychopaths. The task they performed was the go/no-go (GNG) task, which requires one to control their impulses. They chose this task because impulsivity is an important risk factor for recidivism (6223). They focused on ACC activity because this region of the brain has been associated with “error processing, conflict monitoring, response selection, and avoidance-learning,” so it would seem logical that its activity would correlate with performance on the GNG task (6223). Aharoni et al. found that lowered ACC activity on this task was indeed associated with increased probability of rearrest (6224). Interestingly enough, PCL-R Factor 2 score and the prison release age showed similar predictive power, though only for non-violent crimes (6224).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;methodological-and-scientific-concerns&quot;&gt;Methodological and Scientific Concerns&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These three examples all provide interesting proofs of concept for how neuroimaging can be applied to identifying psychopaths and predicting recidivism. However, there are many issues with these examples. I will address the technical issues of each study in turn, and then address more general scientific issues with these types of studies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the machine learning study, the first thing to note is that the classifier based on grey matter density and volume was slightly &lt;em&gt;worse&lt;/em&gt; at discriminating between psychopathic and healthy individuals than the classifier based simply on age and IQ. This shows us how rudimentary our analysis techniques currently are. In the rsfMRI study, we must remember that functional connectivity doesn’t mean two brain regions are functionally connected; it simply means that there’s a correlation in the BOLD signal of the two areas, so we ought to be cautious in our interpretation of this study. Finally, in the ACC activity study, only 9 of the 96 participants later recidivated and were arrested, and therefore we can’t draw huge conclusions from this study because of the problem of false positives (Aharoni, 6224). Furthermore, just because ACC activity on the GNG task seemed to correlate with recidivism, this doesn’t necessarily mean it is causing recidivism, and we ought to keep this in mind when trying to intervene and rehabilitate criminals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a couple issues common to all these studies. All of them were done with prison populations (and in the machine learning case, with incarcerated adolescents). Therefore, we can’t necessarily extend the findings to the general population. This relates to the problem of within-group analyses: just because we see certain levels of brain activity correlate with psychopathy or increased recidivism within a prison population, this doesn’t mean the same will be true for the general population. That said, the machine learning and rsfMRI studies actually did between group analyses, so this strengthens their findings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another concern with all these studies is how they categorize psychopathy. As mentioned before, psychopathy is a disorder composed of many traits, and treating it as one singular disorder is problematic. In the rsfMRI study, even among psychopaths there was a dissociation between Factor 1 and Factor 2 traits of psychopathy and their neural correlates. Therefore, future research ought to be aware that the etiology of each factor can vary, and this will affect how we try to treat different types of psychopathy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A final concern relating to the actual application of this neuroimaging is the risk of false positives and the problem of extending these findings to individuals. Even if we do find some sort of correlation between ACC activity and recidivism in the ACC study, this doesn’t necessarily mean that a single individual with lower ACC activity on the GNG task is more likely to recidivate. Furthermore, in the case of identifying psychopaths, the potential for false positives—that is, identifying someone as a psychopath when they aren’t one—is high, even if the technique has a high overall accuracy. Therefore, we must be cautious in applying these techniques. That said, I see nothing wrong with applying neuroprediction to individuals if we have low p-values, do between-group comparisons, and replicate our results. Current actuarial risk assessment models take into account a host of probabilistic factors that are out of our control, so I don’t see what’s wrong with using neuroimaging in the same way if the technique is thoroughly vetted. In fact, I believe that while not there yet, these neuroimaging techniques will soon have greater construct validity than other measures we currently use in our violence risk assessment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ethical-concerns-is-neuroimaging-special-per-se&quot;&gt;Ethical Concerns: Is Neuroimaging Special Per Se?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one ethical concern unique to neuroimages is that they might bias us, specifically in a legal setting where stakes are high. For example, Weisberg et al. (2008) showed that adding irrelevant neuroscientific information to a bad explanation made lay people find the explanation to be satisfying and logically sound. Furthermore, McCabe and Castel (2008) showed that explanations accompanied by neuroimages were judged as more credible than those not accompanied by neuroimages, suggesting that neuroimages have a special ability to cloud our judgement. One might think that given this biasing effect of neuroimages, we ought not use them in a legal setting. However, Schweitzer et al. (2013) had a significantly larger and more diverse subject pool (over 1000 participants vs. around 150 participants) and were unable to replicate McCabe and Castel’s findings (508). A recent review article by Roskies et al. (2013) also supports this claim, saying that “neuroimages have no special impact on juror decision-making beyond the neuroscientific testimony” (100). That is, the neuroimages themselves are no more biasing than the verbal testimony of a neuroscientist, which is an admissible form of evidence in court (Sinnott-Armstrong et al., 2008).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;applications-and-conclusion&quot;&gt;Applications and Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other than the potential biasing effect of neuroimages, which seems to have been handled, with regards to predicting recidivism and diagnosing psychopathy, neuroimages don’t seem to bring any unique ethical concerns to the table. Nadelhoffer et al. (2012b) and others have argued that the real issue with neuroprediction is “the increased power of prediction, not the fact that neural information is being used to make the prediction” (636). Neuroimaging is simply refining our focus, allowing us to see more. We may not like what we see and may not want to act on that information, but we at least ought to know what is actually there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine that we had a perfect predictive tool that could tell you the probability of a criminal recidivating and within what time period. How would we use this information? Would we even want to know this information? The information itself isn’t bad; it simply has the potential to be applied in bad ways. That said, I’d argue that we’re ethically obligated to use this predictive information in our sentencing, for if we know that someone is likely to recidivate, we ought not to let them back into society until they have been treated and rehabilitated (which neuroimaging can help with). This makes sense within a restorative or consequentialist criminal justice framework—one which cares about rehabilitating criminals and maximizing collective well-being—but doesn’t make much sense in a retributive criminal justice framework—one which cares only about punishing wrongdoers (Greene &amp;amp; Cohen, 2004).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this consequentialist logic can lead us to some dark places. For example, in capital sentencing, if two people committed the same crime and we find out from the neuroimaging data that one is more likely to recidivate, ought we kill this person but keep the other on death row? Irrespective of one’s opinion about the death penalty, it makes sense to spend the resources on the person who is less likely to recidivate, for if they are eventually found innocent then they will cause less harm to society. However, one could imagine a case in which the person who is executed was actually innocent, yet we never found out because we executed them so soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All that said, these ethical issues are not unique to neuroimaging; they are issues we face with any sort of predictive evidence within a utilitarian framework. With the advent of new types of analyses and neuroimaging such as MVPA and rsfMRI, our neuropredictive powers are quickly improving, and if we scrutinize them thoroughly then I think they ought to be a part of our actuarial risk assessment models, which should factor into our criminal sentencing and rehabilitation processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;Citations:&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aharoni, Eyal, Gina M. Vincent, Carla L. Harenski, Vince D. Calhoun, Walter Sinnott-Armstrong, Michael S. Gazzaniga, and Kent A. Kiehl. 2013. “Neuroprediction of Future Rearrest.” &lt;em&gt;Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences&lt;/em&gt; 110(15): 6223-6228.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ennis, Bruce J., and Thomas R. Litwack. 1974. “Psychiatry and the Presumption of Expertise: Flipping Coins in the Courtroom.” &lt;em&gt;California Law Review&lt;/em&gt; 62(3): 693-752.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Greene, Joshua, and Jonathan Cohen. 2004. “For the Law, Neuroscience Changes Nothing and Everything.” &lt;em&gt;Philisophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London B&lt;/em&gt; 359: 1775-1785.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hulbert, Sarah, and Hojjat Adeli. 2015. “Spotting Psychopaths Using Technology.” &lt;em&gt;Review of Neuroscience&lt;/em&gt; 26(6): 721-732.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jones, Owen D., René Marois, Martha J. Farah, and Henry T. Greely. 2013. “Law and Neuroscience.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Neuroscience&lt;/em&gt; 33(45): 17624-17630.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kiehl, Kent. 2010. “Can Neuroscience Identify Pscyhopaths?” &lt;em&gt;A Judge’s Guide to Neuroscience: A Concise Introduction&lt;/em&gt;, ed. Michael Gazzaniga. Law and Neuroscience Project: Nashville, TN.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Koenigs, Michael, Arielle Baskin-Sommers, Joshua D. Zeier, and Joseph P. Newman. 2010. “Investigating the Neural Correlates of Psychopathy: A Critical Review.” &lt;em&gt;Molecular Psychiatry&lt;/em&gt; 16(8): 792-799.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;McCabe, David P., and Alan D. Castel. 2008. “Seeing is Believing: The Effect of Brain Images on Judgements of Scientific Reasoning.” &lt;em&gt;Cognition&lt;/em&gt; 107(1): 343-352.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nadelhoffer, Thomas, Stephanos Bibas, Scott Grafton, Kent A. Kiehl, Andrew Mansfield, Walter Sinnott-Armstrong, and Michael Gazzaniga. 2012a. “Neuroprediction, Violence, and the Law: Setting the Stage.” &lt;em&gt;Neuroethics&lt;/em&gt; 5: 67-99.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nadelhoffer, Thomas, and Walter Sinnott-Armstrong. 2012b. “Neurolaw and Neuroprediction: Potential Promises and Perils.” &lt;em&gt;Philosophy Compass&lt;/em&gt; 7(9): 631-642.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Philippi, Carissa L., Maia S. Pujara, Julian C. Motzkin, Joseph Newman, Kent A. Kiehl, and Michael Koenigs. 2015. “Altered Resting-state Functional Connectivity in Cortical Networks in Psychopathy.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Neuroscience&lt;/em&gt; 35(15): 6068–6078.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roskies, Adina L., N. J. Schweitzer, and Michael J. Saks. 2013. “Neuroimages in Court: Less Biasing than Feared.” &lt;em&gt;Trends in Cognitive Science&lt;/em&gt; 17(3): 99-101.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sato, João R., Ricardo de Oliveira-Souza, Carlos E. Thomaz, Rodrigo Basílio, Ivanei E. Bramati, Edson Amaro Jr., Fernanda Tovar-Moll, Robert D. Hare, and Jorge Moll. 2011. “Identification of Psychopathic Individuals Using Pattern Classification of MRI Images.” &lt;em&gt;Social Neuroscience&lt;/em&gt; 6(5-6): 627–639. ‘&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schweitzer, Nick J., Denise A. Baker, and Evan F. Risko. 2013. “Fooled by the Brain: Re-examining the Influence of Neuroimages.” &lt;em&gt;Cognition&lt;/em&gt; 129: 501-511.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sinnott-Armstrong, Walter, Adina Roskies, Teneille Brown, and Emily Murphy. 2008. “Brain Images as Legal Evidence.” &lt;em&gt;Episteme&lt;/em&gt; 5(3): 359-372.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Steele, Vaughn R., Vikram Rao, Vince D. Calhoun, and Kent A. Kiehl. 2015. “Machine Learning of Structural Magnetic Resonance Imaging Predicts Psychopathic Traits in Adolescent Offenders.” &lt;em&gt;Neuroimage&lt;/em&gt;, in press.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tong, Frank, and Michael S. Pratte. 2012. “Decoding Patterns of Human Brain Activity.” &lt;em&gt;Annual Review of Psychology&lt;/em&gt; 63: 483-509.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weisberg, Deena S., Frank C. Keil, Joshua Goodstein, Elizabeth Rawson, and Jeremy R. Gray. 2008. “The Seductive Allure of Neuroscience Explanations.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Cognitive Neuroscience&lt;/em&gt; 20(3): 470-477.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Image credit: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/nova/next/body/theres-hope-for-fmri-despite-major-software-flaws/&quot;&gt;PBS&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Intro The intersection of cognitive neuroscience and the law—called neurolaw—is a rapidly growing field of research. Many are excited by the potential of neuroscience to improve everything from criminal sentencing to rehabilitation of criminals (Jones et al., 2013). In this paper I will focus on the application of neuroimaging to psychopathy, and specifically on how it can be used to predict future recidivism—aptly named neuroprediction—and identify psychopaths.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why Depression Might Be Adaptive</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/evolution-depression/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Depression Might Be Adaptive" /><published>2017-05-28T15:41:09-04:00</published><updated>2017-05-28T15:41:09-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/evolution-depression</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/evolution-depression/">&lt;p&gt;Major depressive disorder is the most common psychiatric disorder in the United States, affecting 18% of adults (ADAA). Those with depression are lethargic, withdraw from social relationships, and don’t get pleasure from typically enjoyable activities such as eating and sex—a symptom called anhedonia (Watson &amp;amp; Andrews). All this might lead you to believe that depression is maladaptive, some vestigial structure that somehow slipped through the cracks of time. If depression were purely maladaptive, then yes, it would be quite perplexing that it’s so common. However, many have theorized about adaptive explanations for depression, reasons why it may have increased individuals’ fitness and thus persisted. I’ll present and review a couple of these hypotheses—the analytic rumination hypothesis and the inflammation hypothesis—and touch upon some big themes in evolutionary medicine such as tradeoffs, genetics, and evolutionary mismatch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The analytic rumination hypothesis is part of a much broader class of social adaptationist hypotheses about depression (Gilbert). It posits that one of the hallmarks of depression, rumination, was actually adaptive because it allowed for sustained problem-solving and high-level analytical thought. The anhedonia, appetite suppression and lethargy characteristic of depression are features, not bugs, because they allow for this energetically costly problem-solving to happen uninterrupted (Andrews &amp;amp; Thomson Jr.). Because we are social creatures, in our evolutionary past these problems would have been social in nature: analyzing what others think of you, knowing who is allied with whom, etc. Being able to ruminate on these problems for long periods of time would have allowed for better navigation of one’s social scene, which presumably would increase fitness. This hypothesis is further strengthened by the fact that social conflict is highly correlated with the onset of a depressive period, suggesting that depressive rumination is specifically about social problem-solving (Watson &amp;amp; Andrews; Coyne &amp;amp; Downey).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While appealing, Watson and Thomson’s hypothesis needs more evidence in order for it to be a fully fleshed-out theory and not just an evolutionary “just-so story.” One such line of evidence comes from neurophysiology. Depression is often attributed to an imbalance of neurotransmitters in the brain, specifically serotonin. Those with depression have malfunctioning serotonin receptors and often take SSRI’s—a class of medications which improve one’s receptivity to serotonin—because of imbalance of neurotransmitters. Andrews and Thomson point out that this reduced serotonin receptivity in those with depression may actually make attention—an energetically costly cognitive function key to problem-solving—less energetically costly, and thus more sustainable (Andrews &amp;amp; Thomson Jr.). The neurophysiological literature seems to bear this out, and this evidence fits in neatly with the analytical rumination hypothesis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the analytical rumination hypothesis is provocative, some think that it is barking up the wrong tree and that depression’s adaptive value is immunological, not social. A meta-analysis by Barnes et al. found that genetic variations associated with depression seem to correspond with key variations in immune system function (Barnes et al.) Specifically, Gene Wide Association Studies (GWAS)—which look at the whole genome of a population and identify correlations between diseases and specific genes and polymorphisms—find that many of the polymorphisms associated with depression affect key parts of our immune system such as cytokines (Raison &amp;amp; Miller). They argue that in our evolutionary past, those with depression would have greater inflammatory responses to pathogens, decreasing the likelihood of the pathogen’s survival, thus improving the fitness of the depressive host. Furthermore, the behavioral symptoms of depression such as social withdrawal may have prevented our ancestors from being exposed to pathogen and increased their likelihood of survival (Raison and Miller, The Atlantic). This hypothesis is strengthened by evidence showing a high rate of co-occurrence between autoimmune diseases (which affect the immune system) and mood disorders such as depression (Benros et al.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously the etiology of depression is quite complex, as are its symptoms, and I’ve only touched the tip of the iceberg. In this blog I’ve used one term, “depression,” to cover a disorder whose symptoms range from mild lethargy to suicidality, but in reality a fully fleshed out explanation of depression would have to talk about the various gradations and intensities of depression. That said, hopefully a better understanding of the distal, evolutionary causes of depression can improve our treatment of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;References:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ADAA (Anxiety and Depression Association of America). 2016. “Facts and Statistics.” &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.adaa.org/about-adaa/press-room/facts-statistics&quot;&gt;https://www.adaa.org/about-adaa/press-room/facts-statistics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Allen, Nicholas B., and Paul B.T. Badcock. 2006. “Darwinian models of depression: A review of evolutionary accounts of mood and mood disorders.” &lt;em&gt;Progress in Neuro-Psychopharmacology &amp;amp; Biological Psychiatry&lt;/em&gt; 30: 815-826.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Andrews, Paul W., and J. Anderson Thomson Jr. 2009. “The bright side of being blue: depression as an adaptation for analyzing complex problems.” &lt;em&gt;Psychological Review&lt;/em&gt; 116(3): 620-654.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Barnes, J., Mondelli, V., and C.M. Pariante. 2017. “Genetic contributions of inflammation to depression.” &lt;em&gt;Neuropsychopharmacology&lt;/em&gt; 42(1): 81-98.__&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Benros, Michael E., Waltoft, Berit L., Nordentoft, Merete, Østergaard, Søren D., Eaton, William E., Krogh, Jesper, and Preben B. Mortensen. 2013. “Autoimmune diseases and severe infections as risk factors for mood disorders: a nationwide study.” &lt;em&gt;JAMA Psychiatry&lt;/em&gt; 70(8): 812-820.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coyne, James C., and Geraldine Downey. 1991. “Social factors and psychopathology: stress, social support, and coping processes.” &lt;em&gt;Annual Review of Psychology&lt;/em&gt; 42: 401-425.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gilbert, Paul. 2006. “Evolution and depression: issues and implications.” &lt;em&gt;Psychological Medicine&lt;/em&gt; 36: 287-297.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Raison, C.L., and A.H. Miller. 2013. “The evolutionary significance of depression in Pathogen Host Defense (PATHOS-D).” &lt;em&gt;Molecular Psychiatry&lt;/em&gt; 18: 15-37.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Watson, Paul J., and Paul W. Andrews. 2002. “Toward a revised evolutionary and adaptationist analysis of depression: the social navigation hypothesis.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Affective Disorders&lt;/em&gt; 72: 1-14.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Major depressive disorder is the most common psychiatric disorder in the United States, affecting 18% of adults (ADAA). Those with depression are lethargic, withdraw from social relationships, and don’t get pleasure from typically enjoyable activities such as eating and sex—a symptom called anhedonia (Watson &amp;amp; Andrews). All this might lead you to believe that depression is maladaptive, some vestigial structure that somehow slipped through the cracks of time. If depression were purely maladaptive, then yes, it would be quite perplexing that it’s so common. However, many have theorized about adaptive explanations for depression, reasons why it may have increased individuals’ fitness and thus persisted. I’ll present and review a couple of these hypotheses—the analytic rumination hypothesis and the inflammation hypothesis—and touch upon some big themes in evolutionary medicine such as tradeoffs, genetics, and evolutionary mismatch.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">You (Probably) Aren’t Conscious Right Now</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/conscious-pt-1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="You (Probably) Aren’t Conscious Right Now" /><published>2017-04-14T15:54:07-04:00</published><updated>2017-04-14T15:54:07-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/you-arent-conscious-right-now</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/conscious-pt-1/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;My first foray into philosophy of mind, c. 2017; a followup essay, which extends these concepts, can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://adamlgreen.com/searching-for-self/&quot;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I write this paper it seems as if I am undergoing a set of sensory experiences. I pick up my mug and &lt;em&gt;feel&lt;/em&gt; its warmth in my hand; I &lt;em&gt;taste&lt;/em&gt; the coffee; I &lt;em&gt;hear&lt;/em&gt; the pitter-patter of the rain outside my window. These experiences all seem to have distinctly mental properties such as phenomenality—there is something it is &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; for me to be undergoing these experiences—subjectivity—&lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; am the one undergoing these experiences—and privacy—I have &lt;em&gt;special first-person knowledge&lt;/em&gt; of these experiences that others don’t. While these properties may seem metaphysically special, I will argue that they, and all other mental properties, are not special. The specialness of these properties is an illusion, one which is so convincing and pervasive that it is nearly impossible to see through, but ultimately these properties are nothing more than complex physical properties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll provide a summary of my view of the natural world: I am a physicalist. I don’t believe in the existence of immaterial souls, ghosts or ghouls, and thus am firmly opposed to substance dualism. I believe that we can learn about the natural world by testing falsifiable claims and providing evidence to support these claims. That said, we can never truly prove a claim; the best we will ever get is a plausible explanation, not certainty. Therefore, scientific claims are provisional and subject to change. In my argument, I rely heavily on evolutionary theory (i.e. the principles of evolution via natural selection), which I believe is an example of such a scientific theory that makes falsifiable and testable claims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s how the paper is structured. In Part 1, I’ll define important terms and discuss Levine’s “explanatory gap”. In Part 2, I’ll propose four possible evolutionary explanations of the mental. In Part 3, I’ll discuss the adaptive value of theory of mind and explain the Attention Schema Theory, a potential explanation of how the illusion of subjectivity arises from purely physical processes. Finally, I will address objections to my argument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-explanatory-gap&quot;&gt;The Explanatory Gap&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will use the term &lt;em&gt;the mental&lt;/em&gt; to refer to the class of properties which folk psychology classifies as metaphysically special as compared to purely physical properties: phenomenality, subjectivity, intentionality, etc. I will interchangeably use the terms &lt;em&gt;consciousness&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;subjectivity&lt;/em&gt; to refer to state consciousness—that is, mental states that possess these mental properties (Van Gulick, &lt;em&gt;Consciousness&lt;/em&gt;). Under my definition, consciousness encompasses both sensations and propositional attitudes, though my argument is focused on sensations. The definitions I’ve provided are quite nebulous. By the end of this paper I hope to show you that this is for good reason: while useful abstractions, talk of the mental and consciousness is ultimately as absurd as talk of spirits or ghosts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we can reduce physical phenomena (e.g. a baseball player throwing a baseball) down to physics and chemistry, most people agree that there is special class of things which possess properties that can’t be explained via the same physics and chemistry: the mental. No matter how much we know about the physics of echolocation or the flavor profile of insects, it seems that we can never truly understand “what it is like” to be a bat, for example (Nagel, 1974, 437). There is a certain first-person subjectivity, a distinct phenomenal character of the bat’s experience that we can never understand in the same way it does. In folk psychology, we call this property &lt;em&gt;phenomenality&lt;/em&gt;. Even as our neuroscience and psychology advances, materialism seems to be left with this intractable epistemological problem of explaining these mental properties in purely physical terms. Levine calls this “the explanatory gap” (Levine, 1983, 360).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the explanatory gap seems obviously insurmountable, I will argue that it is not. It only seems insurmountable because we are so entrenched in folk psychology and talk of the mental that we can’t look at the mental in a sober manner. To understand the mental, we ought to question what causes its existence to seem so obvious to us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;four-explanations-of-the-mental&quot;&gt;Four Explanations of the Mental&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mental properties didn’t just pop up out of nowhere. Like any physical property, such as the ability to breath air, mental properties need to have arisen somewhere in our evolutionary development to be consistent with a naturalistic explanation of the world. This could have occurred in four possible ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A supernatural being like a god gave us these mental properties, and thus they are still metaphysically special.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mental properties are an emergent property of complex information-processing which arose somewhere in our evolutionary development, and thus the mental is still special.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Our ancestors, all the way back to single-cell organisms, had the precursors of mental properties; therefore, mental properties are graded yet still special.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Metaphysically special mental properties never actually arose in our evolutionary development. They are an illusion, and thus we don’t have them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can discard the first explanation, as it isn’t consistent with naturalism; the third explanation, the panprotopsychist explanation, seems just as absurd so we can discard it too. [&lt;em&gt;Note: due to word count, I was unable to provide a fully fleshed out objection to panprotopsychism; ideally I would have explained why I think it is absurd, rather than dismiss the idea with a single sentence]&lt;/em&gt;. While the second explanation seems sensible, I will argue that if we probe deeper we will see it is has some holes. Firstly, at what point in our evolutionary history did these mental properties arise? We face an infinite regress problem here. No matter where you point in our evolutionary history, from the development of nervous systems or the genus &lt;em&gt;Homo&lt;/em&gt;, we still face an (evolutionary) explanatory gap. As this might lead you to believe, perhaps mental properties never arose in our evolutionary history and explanation four is correct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;illusions-theory-of-mind-and-the-attention-schema-theory&quot;&gt;Illusions, Theory of Mind, and the Attention Schema Theory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While explanation four logically makes sense, it runs counter to our intuitions about the mental. Surely you are conscious as you read this: how couldn’t you be? As I hope to show, this consciousness—a mental property which we attribute to our self and others—is an illusion, a trick the human brain plays on itself (Frankish, 2016).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, let’s address theory of mind—our attribution of mental properties and minds to other people—which is the core of folk psychology. Do we know that other people have minds and mental properties? No, we do not have proof of this. For all we know, other people could act as if they have minds and mental properties but just be “philosophical zombies” (Kirk, &lt;em&gt;Zombies&lt;/em&gt;). Nevertheless, we still attribute the mental to others because of induction: if I have a mind and am a human being, it seems most parsimonious for other human beings to have minds and not be zombies. However, we ought to doubt the antecedent, for as I will show, the attribution of a mind to our self relies on the exact same sort of induction we use when we attribute minds to others; that is, we don’t have any sort of privileged first-person knowledge of our own mind that would allow us to use induction to infer that others have similar minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-adaptive-value-of-believing-in-mental-properties&quot;&gt;The Adaptive Value of Believing in Mental Properties&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To show that minds and mental properties are an illusion, I will first explain the adaptive value of believing in them. Consider trying to develop an atom-for-atom representation of another human being whom you are competing with. For a human brain, this is computationally impossible. However, when you abstract and use heuristics such as the concept of a “mind” or a “person” you can predict the behavior of other humans. Thus, theory of mind is simply a heuristic which facilitates cooperation, increasing the evolutionary fitness—that is, surviving and producing fertile offspring—of the individual and the species. What differentiates humans from most other species is our complex social behavior, which is predicated on theory of mind. Thus, theory of mind is a useful and evolutionarily adaptive heuristic, but that doesn’t necessarily mean that it’s a realistic representation of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back at our evolutionary history, we can see the progression from simple neuronal competition to full-fledged theory of mind. It all began roughly 700 million years ago, when our animal lineage split off from the lineage of animals without nervous systems, such as the sponge (Graziano &amp;amp; Webb, 2017, 547). We then see the development of the precursor of attention, “selective signal enhancement,” in which neurons compete for their signal to beat out the signal of other neurons; those neurons that win have their signals amplified and those that lose have their signals diminished (Graziano, 2014, 1300). This enhancement is bottom-up. Conversely, the top-down control of which signals are enhanced later developed, and we call this top-down control &lt;em&gt;attention&lt;/em&gt; (Graziano, 2017, 548). If you’re asked to find Waldo among a crowd of people, you are exerting attention, turning up the gain on neurons which are tuned to certain red and white visual stimuli and turning down the gain on neurons tuned to other visual stimuli.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;subjectivity-as-a-mental-schema&quot;&gt;Subjectivity as a Mental Schema&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Per the Attention Schema Theory proposed by Webb and Graziano, the metaphysically special mental property we call subjectivity “is the brain’s internal model of the process of attention” (Webb &amp;amp; Graziano, 2015, 1). That is, awareness is a &lt;em&gt;mental schema&lt;/em&gt;, a construct which facilitates our ability to control attention and leads to the illusion of subjectivity. Attention is the top-down control of how our neurons process incoming stimuli, and awareness is our model of this process (Webb &amp;amp; Graziano, 2015, 2).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, when we drink coffee, our taste buds are stimulated, leading to a certain pattern of brain activity. Perhaps we like coffee, so certain neurotransmitters are released in the brain and we emit an audible “yum”. Here there is a causal relationship between the physical process of drinking the coffee and our physiological reactions to it. Only when we apply the schema of awareness and the schema of the self to these physical processes do we begin to believe that we are undergoing a sensory experience composed of metaphysically special properties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this belief need not mean that we are actually undergoing a phenomenal experience. As stated before, the apparent phenomenality of our experience comes from attributing this mental schema called &lt;em&gt;awareness&lt;/em&gt; to ourselves (Webb &amp;amp; Graziano, 2015, 6). This is the same schema we attribute to others as part of theory of mind. Thus, we don’t have any privileged first-person access to our own mental life; this first-person perspective is simply a consequence of our mental schema.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evidence for the Attention Schema Theory comes from the psychology of illusions. In one experiment, subjects’ view of their left hand and arm is occluded by a screen, and they are told to focus on a rubber arm and hand placed in front of them. The experimenters simultaneously brush the real arm and the rubber arm for ten minutes. Subjects report that “they seemed to feel the touch not of the hidden brush but that of the viewed brush, as if the rubber hand had sensed the touch” (Botvinick &amp;amp; Cohen, 1998, 756). In this example, the schema subjects had of their body—the “body schema”—was fooled (Webb &amp;amp; Graziano, 2015, 5). We utilize mental schemata to make sense of the world, but as shown by this experiment, these schemata don’t always accurately represent the world as it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meditation and introspection into our “first-person experience” also provide evidence for the illusoriness of subjectivity. If you simply close your eyes and sit there, without explicitly thinking about the fact that you are sitting, what is left? In the present moment, until you attend to the thought that you are sitting or that your nose itches, you don’t have the property of consciousness. As Susan Blackmore argues, “whenever we ask about consciousness, a temporary unit of a set of thoughts and perceptions is constructed and is linked to a representation of the self as a continuing observer” (Blackmore, 2016, 55). But up until that point, there is no metaphysically special property called consciousness to be found.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attributing theory of mind to our self and others has adaptive value; we can track the development of theory of mind across broad swaths of evolutionary time; and we are beginning to explain how the illusion of consciousness arises. I believe that the most parsimonious explanation of all this evidence is that metaphysically special mental properties such as subjectivity and phenomenality don’t exist. Now that we realize the explanatory gap can be bridged, the challenge we face is what Dennett calls “the illusion problem—the problem of explaining how the illusion of phenomenality arises and why it is so powerful” (Dennett, 2016, 65).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;objections&quot;&gt;Objections&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;1. I’m conscious right now, so isn’t this evidence of me possessing mental properties?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I invite you to prove that you are conscious right now. If you probe your first-person experience, then you will see that you do not possess any metaphysically special property called consciousness. You may believe that you are conscious, and I cannot deny that you believe this. However, as stated before, this belief comes not from special first-person knowledge of your mental states, but instead comes from you utilizing a mental schema of attention called awareness, and attributing this awareness to yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While convincing, this schema is as illusory as the existence of free will or the linearity of time. For example, until Einstein came along, we all thought that time was absolute and linear. But we now know that time is intimately tied with space and can dilate depending on your relationship to the earth or another gravitational mass (Markosian, &lt;em&gt;Time&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it’s likely we will have similar revelations in neuroscience and psychology and will someday completely explain the illusion of the mental in purely physical terms. We will look back on mental properties in the same way we look back on properties such as &lt;em&gt;being phlogistonated&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;having an imbalance of humors&lt;/em&gt;: as useful yet absurd, pre-theoretical constructs that we should have dispensed with a long time ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;2. If no organism has a mind, doesn’t this invalidate the existence of moral truth? Wouldn’t this give us license to be cruel to humans and non-human animals, increasing the net suffering in the world?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would agree that there is no objective moral truth. Like theory of mind, morality is merely an evolutionary adaptation. Specifically, it is a way to deal with the free-rider problem, and we too can come up with convincing explanations of how it evolved and why it’s adaptive (Hardin, &lt;em&gt;The Free Rider Problem&lt;/em&gt;). That said, my argument here isn’t normative. I don’t condone purposefully increasing the net suffering in the world. Humans seem to have reached a peak on the complexity landscape, and therefore perhaps the human project is special and something we ought to try to maintain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;3. Doesn’t this mean that we could program machines to be conscious?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, a machine could be conscious insofar as we are conscious; that is, we would call it conscious and say it has subjective experience, but it wouldn’t possess any metaphysically special mental properties. It would be performing the same sorts actions we do, just in silico.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;References:&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blackmore, Susan. 2016. “Delusions of Consciousness.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Consciousness Studies&lt;/em&gt;, 23(11): 52–64.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Botvinick, Matthew, and Jonathan Cohen. 1998. “Rubber Hands ‘Feel’ Touch That Eyes See.” &lt;em&gt;Nature&lt;/em&gt; 391(19): 756.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dennett, Daniel C. 2016. “Illusionism as the Obvious Default Theory of Consciousness.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Consciousness Studies&lt;/em&gt;, 23(11): 65–72.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frankish, Keith. 2016. “Illusionism as a Theory of Consciousness.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Consciousness Studies&lt;/em&gt;, 23(11): 11–39.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graziano, Michael S. A. 2014. “Speculations on the Evolution of Awareness.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Cognitive Neuroscience&lt;/em&gt;, 26(6): 1300–1304.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Graziano, Michael S. A., and Taylor W. Webb. 2017. “From Sponge to Human: The Evolution of Consciousness.” In &lt;em&gt;Evolution of Nervous Systems (Volume 3)&lt;/em&gt;, ed. Jon Kaas. Elsevier: Oxford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hardin, Russell. “The Free Rider Problem.” &lt;em&gt;The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy&lt;/em&gt; (Spring 2013 Edition), ed. Edward N. Zalta. &lt;a href=&quot;https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/spr2013/entries/free-rider/&quot;&gt;https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/spr2013/entries/free-rider/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kirk, Robert. “Zombies.” &lt;em&gt;The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy&lt;/em&gt; (Summer 2015 Edition), ed. Edward N. Zalta. &lt;a href=&quot;https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/sum2015/entries/zombies/&quot;&gt;https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/sum2015/entries/zombies/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Levine, Joseph. 1983. “Materialism and Qualia: The Explanatory Gap.” &lt;em&gt;Pacific Philosophical Quarterly&lt;/em&gt;, 64: 354–361.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Markosian, Ned. “Time.” &lt;em&gt;The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy&lt;/em&gt; (Fall 2016 Edition), ed. Edward N. Zalta. &lt;a href=&quot;https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/fall2016/entries/time/&quot;&gt;https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/fall2016/entries/time/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nagel, Thomas. 1974. “What Is It Like to Be a Bat?” &lt;em&gt;The Philosophical Review&lt;/em&gt;, 83(4): 435–450.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Serino, Andrea, Alsmith, Adrian, Constantini, Marcello, Mandrigin, Alisa, Tajadura-Jimenez, Ana, and Christopher Lopez. 2013. “Bodily Ownership and Self-Location: Components of Bodily Self-Consciousness.” &lt;em&gt;Consciousness and Cognition&lt;/em&gt;, 22: 1239–1252.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Webb, Taylor W., and Michael S. A. Graziano. 2015. “The Attention Schema Theory: A Mechanistic Account of Subjective Awareness.” &lt;em&gt;Frontiers in Psychology&lt;/em&gt;, 5(500): 1–11.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Van Gulick, Robert. “Consciousness.” &lt;em&gt;The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy&lt;/em&gt; (Winter 2016 Edition), ed. Edward N. Zalta. &lt;a href=&quot;https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/win2016/entries/consciousness/&quot;&gt;https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/win2016/entries/consciousness/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">My first foray into philosophy of mind, c. 2017; a followup essay, which extends these concepts, can be found here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Does Believing in Free Will May Make You Punish More Harshly?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/punishment-and-free-will/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Does Believing in Free Will May Make You Punish More Harshly?" /><published>2016-12-27T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2016-12-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/tpp-and-free-will</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/punishment-and-free-will/">&lt;p&gt;Philosophers have long debated about free will—are we in control of our actions or are they ultimately predetermined? Regardless of what the answer to this question is, recent work in moral psychology shows that our beliefs about agency affect our decision-making. Krueger et al. (2014) explored how belief in free will—which they termed “BFW”—affects our decisions about third-party punishment—which they termed “TPP” (1143). Third-party punishment is a way of punishing those who violate social norms; in TPP, rather than have the person wronged choose and execute the punishment of the wrongdoer, this responsibility is given to an impartial decision-maker such as a judge or court system (1143). Krueger et al. collected behavioral and fMRI data on how BFW affects choice of TPP for a variety of criminal actions. They also examined how the affect of a crime—that is, its emotional salience—impacted choice of punishment. Their paper demonstrates how reverse inference can be done well and shows that our discussions about free will have real-world consequences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the Free Will and Determinism questionnaire (Paulhus &amp;amp; Carey, 2011), Krueger et al. divided up their subjects into libertarians—those who have BFW—and determinists—those who don’t have BFW. In the experiment, subjects were placed in an fMRI machine and presented with a series of written criminal scenarios, ranging from theft to rape and murder. They were then asked to choose, on a scale from 0 to 100, the appropriate level of punishment the criminal deserved for committing each crime. Subjects were also asked to rate their “subjective affective experience” of each scenario. This metric captured the emotional valence and arousal level elicited by the scenario. Using this information, they divided the criminal scenarios into a “low affective” and a “high affective” group (1144).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Krueger et al. found that for low affective crimes, libertarians punished more severely (10% so) and displayed significantly greater activation in the right tempo-parietal junction (rTPJ) than determinists. They posited that the libertarians display greater activation because the rTPJ is “probably involved in the…attribution of temporary intentions and beliefs of others” (1147). Thus, the libertarians punished more severely than the determinists for the low affective crimes because they felt the criminals were more responsible for their actions (1147). However, for high affective crimes libertarians and determinists punished similarly and showed similar levels of rTPJ activation. Both also showed increased activation in the right anterior insula (rAI), an area involved in “aversive interoceptive-emotional processing”—that is, internal awareness of negative emotions—as well as feelings of moral disgust (1147-1148). The rTPJ and the rAI are both part of the salience network of our brain which dictates what we attend to, and Krueger et al. argue that they compete in a winner-take-all fashion (1148). Thus, determinists and libertarians punished similarly for the high affective crimes because the scenarios elicited an extreme, negative emotional response which dominated processing (1148).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper has a similar flavor to Greene et al.’s (2001; 2005) work on the dual-process theory of moral judgements. As is the case with Greene et al., one might be a bit skeptical of the reverse inferences made by Krueger et al., especially after reading Poldrack (2006). Poldrack claims that reverse inferences—inferring that a task involves a cognitive function because the task causes increased activity in a brain region associated with that function—are epistemically weak because a single brain region can be involved in many cognitive functions. Thus, according to Poldrack, if we do want to make a reverse inference, we must account for all the cases in which that area of the brain is active yet the cognitive function of interest is not recruited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making a perfect Bayesian reverse inference as Poldrack would like requires knowing all the possible brain states in which our brain region of interest is active; however, this is impossible, as there could be an infinite number of cases in which it is active. Therefore, all we can do is try to make better, rather than worse, reverse inferences. Krueger et al. do so by providing multiple lines of converging evidence. For example, they discuss a previous study in which transcranial magnetic stimulation to the rTPJ “caused subjects to judge attempted harms as less morally forbidden and more morally permissible” (1147). This supports their inference about why determinists showed lower rTPJ activation and punished less severely as compared to the libertarians for low affective crimes. They also cite work which shows that the rAI and the rTPJ are “structurally and functionally connected to each other,” supporting their claim that these regions compete with one another to dominate processing (1147).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Krueger et al.’s reverse inferences are also strong because they focus on small areas—the rTPJ and rAI—with specialized functions— “aversive interoceptive-emotional processing” and “attribution of temporary intentions and beliefs of others”—as opposed to broader functions such as ‘emotion’ or ‘cognition’ (1147). Furthermore, Krueger et al. used psychological surveys to control for confounding variables such as differences in empathy or emotional awareness between libertarians and determinists, which strengthens their experimental design overall (1144). Thus, though the rTPJ and rAI are involved multiple cognitive functions, we have good reason to believe that Krueger et al.’s reverse inferences are justified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some might think that debating about free will is the arcane and unimportant work of philosophers in the ivory tower. However, as this paper shows, BFW impacts our decision-making in important and practical ways. For example, Krueger et al. briefly mention how BFW or lack thereof might bias jurors in a criminal case towards finding a defendant innocent or guilty, depending on the psychological affect of their offense (1148). Though contrived, one could imagine two people being tried for exactly the same low affective crime, yet one faces a jury of determinists and the other a jury of libertarians. Suppose that the former is found innocent and the other guilty. I don’t think we could call such a legal process just. Therefore, in order to eliminate bias, perhaps we should vet jurors by having them perform a series of psychological questionnaires, one of which tests for BFW. Even if we don’t go this far, we should at least be aware that our beliefs can influence our decision-making in unexpected and consequential ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;References:&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Greene, Joshua. 2005. “Emotion and Cognition in Moral Judgement: Evidence from Neuroimaging.” In &lt;em&gt;Neurobiology of Human Values&lt;/em&gt;, ed. Jean-Pierre Changeaux, Antonio R. Damasio, Wolf Singer, and Yves Christen, 57–66. Berlin: Springer-Verlag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Greene, Joshua, R. Brian Sommerville, Leigh E. Nystrom, John M. Darley, and Jonathan D. Cohen. 2001. “An fMRI Investigation of Emotional Engagement in Moral Judgement.” &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt; 293(5537): 2105–2108.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Krueger, Frank, Morris Hoffman, Henrik Walter, and Jordan Grafman. 2014. “An fMRI Investigation of the Effects of Belief in Free-will on Third-party Punishment.” &lt;em&gt;Social Cognitive and Affective Neuroscience&lt;/em&gt; 9(8): 1143–1149.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paulhus, Delroy, and Jasmine Carey. 2011. “The FAD-plus: Measuring Lay Beliefs Regarding Free Will and Related Constructs.” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Personality Assessment&lt;/em&gt; 93(1): 96–104.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Poldrack, Russell A. 2006. “Can Cognitive Processes Be Inferred from Neuroimaging Data?” &lt;em&gt;Trends in Cognitive Science&lt;/em&gt; 10(2): 59–63.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Philosophers have long debated about free will—are we in control of our actions or are they ultimately predetermined? Regardless of what the answer to this question is, recent work in moral psychology shows that our beliefs about agency affect our decision-making. Krueger et al. (2014) explored how belief in free will—which they termed “BFW”—affects our decisions about third-party punishment—which they termed “TPP” (1143). Third-party punishment is a way of punishing those who violate social norms; in TPP, rather than have the person wronged choose and execute the punishment of the wrongdoer, this responsibility is given to an impartial decision-maker such as a judge or court system (1143). Krueger et al. collected behavioral and fMRI data on how BFW affects choice of TPP for a variety of criminal actions. They also examined how the affect of a crime—that is, its emotional salience—impacted choice of punishment. Their paper demonstrates how reverse inference can be done well and shows that our discussions about free will have real-world consequences.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Kin Selection for Alarm Calling Behavior in Rodent Species</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/squirrels/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kin Selection for Alarm Calling Behavior in Rodent Species" /><published>2016-03-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2016-03-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/squirrels-are-cool</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/squirrels/">&lt;blockquote class=&quot;wp-block-quote&quot;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    &quot;I would lay down my life for two brothers or eight cousins.&quot;
  &lt;/p&gt;
  
  &lt;cite&gt; &lt;em&gt;J.B.S. Haldane&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/cite&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the presence of predators, animals such as the Belding’s ground squirrel (&lt;em&gt;Spermophilus beldingi&lt;/em&gt;) will often emit distinct types of vocalizations called “alarm calls” by naturalists (Dunford, 1977, 782). Since the documentation of these alarm calls, biologists have theorized about their adaptive value and what selective pressures gave rise to them. Two camps have emerged in the literature: those who argue that the alarm-calls are an example of kin selection, and others such who argue that they can be explained via individual selection. In this paper I will explore the evolution of alarm calls using the Belding’s ground squirrel as a case study, and then look at alarm calls among rodents in general. I will argue that while alarm calling may have been selected for via kin selection in certain instances, in most cases it evolved because it conferred individual fitness benefits to the caller, and therefore can be explained without reference to higher level selection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sherman (1977) argues that these alarm calls are an example of altruism because they are used to warn relatives of approaching predators but end up endangering the caller, thus lowering his or her individual fitness. His evidence for this conclusion comes from field studies of squirrels’ responses to terrestrial predators such as coyotes, bobcats and weasels. Because of the social structure of these squirrels—females tend to stay and breed near their birthplace until death, whereas males disperse from the area where they were born—female ground squirrels in the same area tend to have a high degree of genetic relatedness, whereas males do not (1248). Thus, Sherman predicted that if kin selection were the mechanism behind these alarm calls, then females would be more likely than males to emit these calls. And indeed, that is what he found: “when a predatory mammal appears, old, reproductive, resident females with living kin are the most likely to call, while males are the most consistent noncallers” (1250). Furthermore, those males who successfully breed, produce progeny, and stay at that location tend to call more than males who were not reproductively successful. Finally, he found that the less living close relatives a female ground squirrel has, the less likely she is to give alarm calls (1249).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This discrimination based on relatedness suggests that kin selection is the mechanism behind alarm calling; therefore, invoking Hamilton’s rule seems appropriate in this case study. In fact, Hamilton actually mentions alarm calls among birds in his famous 1964 paper: “The alarm call of a bird probably involves a small extra risk to the individual making it by rendering it more noticeable to the approaching predator but the consequent reduction of risk to a nearby bird previously unaware of danger must be much greater” (15). The reasons the birds and squirrels take this risk, according to Hamilton and Sherman, is because doing so confers an inclusive fitness benefit to the caller: though they may be endangering themselves by giving the call, doing so warns their relatives—whom they share a lot of genes with—thereby increasing those relatives’ fitness, which indirectly benefits the caller. In principe, this behavior could have evolved via Hamilton’s rule: if squirrels who alarm-call tend to have more living relatives who could pass on their genes, this alarm calling behavior would be propagated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hamilton’s rule working in this case depends on the alarm call being a costly behavior for the caller; however, later work by Sherman (1985) suggests that in some cases alarm calling may not endanger the caller but actually confer an individual fitness benefit upon it. For example, in his study of aerial predation on Belding ground squirrels, Sherman found that giving an alarm call was positively associated with escaping from the predating hawk. One might wonder if we are conflating correlation and causation here, as alarm calls could be a consequence rather than a cause of escape behavior. But in fact, Sherman found that of all squirrels who were spotted by a predator and tried to escape, those who gave alarm calls were more likely to survive than those who did not. This makes one wonder whether kin selection is the only mechanism behind the evolution of alarm calling in Belding ground squirrels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further explanation by Sherman sheds light on this question and suggests that another mechanism may be at play. First, note that there exist two main types of alarm calls—trills in response to the presence of a terrestrial predators, as were mentioned by Sherman (1977), and whistles, which are given when an aerial predator is spotted and are discussed by Sherman (1985). Sherman showed that while the frequency of the former depends on the relatedness of nearby individuals, whistling tendencies “were not affected by sex, age, or kinship” (Sherman, 1985, 320). Furthermore, while trills tend to attract a predator to the caller, resulting in callers being killed more often than noncallers, whistling may be associated with minimal risk or result in the caller being &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; likely to be killed (320). Thus, Sherman argued that these whistles were used to “indicate to attacking raptors that they have been seen, thus discouraging their pursuit” and to “startle the predators,” benefitting the caller, not his or her kin (321). This dichotomy between trills in response to terrestrial predators and whistles in response to aerial predators muddies the waters, and suggests that perhaps the two types of calls evolved via two different selective mechanisms, kin selection and individual selection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to see which of these two hypotheses played a greater role in the evolution of alarm calling more generally, Shelley and Blumstein (2005) examined the relationship between sociality, alarm calling, and diurnality among 209 rodent species. They argued that alarm calling in order to communicate with predators—either to let them know they have been detected or to deter them—is inherently risky, and we would expect rodents to try to minimize the amount of risk they face when performing this behavior. One way to do this is only whistle when one is able to see the predator. Shelley and Blumstein cite earlier field work showing that prey will often “visually assess the relative risk of predation and only call when they are not subjected to excessive risk” (169). Therefore, the authors predicted that if alarm calling evolved because of the individual fitness benefits it conferred (via communication to predators), then alarm calling species should tend to be diurnal rather than nocturnal, because diurnal species would be much better at visual assessment (169). Conversely, the authors argue that “if alarm calling evolved via nepotism, we would expect to see social species (particularly those living near kin) more likely to call than are nonsocial species” (169).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors found that while sociality was highly associated with alarm calling, diurnality “accounted for three to six times as much variation in whether or not a species alarm called than did sociality” (173). The authors also used a phylogenetic tree to reconstruct the evolution of alarm calling among the 209 species. The tree suggested that in all cases “the evolution of diurnality preceded the evolution of alarm calling” (173). These findings, coupled with the authors’ hypothesis that diurnality is critical to communicating with predators because of the necessity of light for visual assessment, suggest that among the 209 rodent species examined, alarm calling originally evolved not to warn kin, but because it offered an individual fitness benefit to the caller. This is not to say that alarm calling is never used to communicate to kin, or that it could not have been selected for via kin selection; however, it does suggest that alarm calling is used as a means of improving one’s own fitness, not the fitness of one’s relatives. So why do we see Belding ground squirrels alerting relatives by alarm calling? The authors conclude that “while alarm calling may have evolved as a means of communicating to predators…in certain species, alarm calling may have also independently evolved to communicate to conspecifics to warn them of danger” (173).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sherman’s (1985) paper on aerial predation and the paper by Shelley and Blumstein both force us to reevaluate a &lt;em&gt;prima facie&lt;/em&gt; case of kin selection. Yes, it seems that one type of alarm call made by Belding ground squirrels could have evolved via kin selection, and Hamilton’s rule would assist in making sense of when these alarm calls would occur. However, what may problematize the application of Hamilton’s rule here is that alarm calling can actually provide a benefit to the caller, which is not accounted for in the equation. If we set individual fitness benefits aside, the selection for this type of nepotistic alarm calling is an example of what Samir Okasha calls MLS1—multi-level selection one—a type of group selection where a phenotype is selected for not because it provides a direct fitness benefit to its holder but because it increases the average fitness of the population, and by extension the caller’s inclusive fitness (Okasha, 1020). However, it seems that alarm call in response to aerial predators, and alarm calls among rodent species more generally, can be accounted for using only individual fitness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;References:&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Christopher Dunford, “Kin Selection for Ground Squirrel Alarm Calls,” &lt;em&gt;The American Naturalist&lt;/em&gt; 111, no. 980 (1977): 782ꟷ785.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;W.D. Hamilton, “The Genetical Evolution of Social Behavior. I,” &lt;em&gt;Journal of Theoretical Biology&lt;/em&gt; 7 (1964): 1ꟷ16.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Samir Okasha, “Multilevel Selection and the Major Transitions in Evolution,” &lt;em&gt;Philosophy of Science&lt;/em&gt; 72, no. 5 (2005): 1013ꟷ1025.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Erin L. Shelley and Daniel T. Blumstein, “The Evolution of Vocal Alarm Communication in Rodents,” &lt;em&gt;Behavioral Ecology&lt;/em&gt; 16, no. 1 (2004): 169ꟷ177.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul W. Sherman, “Nepotism and the Evolution of Alarm Calls,” &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt; 197, no. 4310 (1977): 1246ꟷ1253.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul W. Sherman, “Alarm Calls of Belding’s Ground Squirrels to Aerial Predators: Nepotism or Self-Preservation?” &lt;em&gt;Behavioral Ecology and Sociobiology&lt;/em&gt; 17, no. 4 (1985): 313ꟷ323.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">&quot;I would lay down my life for two brothers or eight cousins.&quot; J.B.S. Haldane</summary></entry></feed>